<part id="admin_gui">
  <title>Administrator Home: Administrator GUI Tools</title>
    <partintro>
    <para>Graphical administration tools are available for &product; and can 
be accessed via the &admin_home; page. When an administrator logs in, 
they are immediately taken to Admin Home. The majority of administrative 
tasks can be accomplished from this location, but there are also command 
line scripts for some tasks to facilitate scripting of administration
tasks.  Additionally, there are some command line scripts for some
functionality that has not yet been integrated into &admin_home;, namely
the management of <link linkend="analysis">analyses</link> and <link
linkend="layout">layouts</link>.
    </para>
    </partintro>

  <article id="&product;_administration">
  <title>&product; Administration</title> 
  <sect1 id="configure_&product;">
  <title>Configure &product;</title>
    <para>This page may be used to set the runtime configuration 
variables for your &product; implementation. This should be done directly after 
an installation. You may occasionally wish to update parameters, but they 
should only require seldom changes (if ever) after installation.  A brief 
description of each parameter follows:
    <variablelist>
      <title>General</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>WWW Host</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          This is the FQDN of the server that &product; is installed on.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
         
      <varlistentry>
        <term id="additional_path">Additional Path Information</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
If you did not set your DocumentRoot to /var/www/html/&product;/site, you 
will need to enter additional path information.  That path information 
should contain the path from HTML_DIR to the site directory.  For instance, 
if your DocumentRoot is /var/www/html, you would set your additional 
path information to /&product;/site.  If this variable is not set
correctly, &product; will be unable to find its web pages correctly.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
         
      <varlistentry>
        <term><link linkend="chip_data_path">Chip Data Path</link></term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
         This specifies the location of chip data files.
         When the <link linkend="array_center_staff_user">array center
         staff user</link>  attempts to load data, the system
         will look for the <link linkend="chip_data_files">chip data
         files</link> in this location and in its subdirectories. 
         The user running the web server needs to have read permission on
         this directory.  Administrators can verify correct permissions
         via the <link
         linkend="&product;_installation_information">&product;
         Installation Information</link> link.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Administrator Email</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        This is the email address of the primary <link
        linkend="administrator_user">Administrator User</link>.
        This email address is provided as a contact for users.
        Additionally, this address is the recipient for automatically
        generated alerts regarding improper system configuration.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Alternate Email</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        Formerly, this email address was cc'd on all correspondence to
        the Array Center Staff Email address.  Currently, the field is 
        not in use, but may be revived if the need arises.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>URL for companion &product; system</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        If an installation does not support all <link
        linkend="users">user</link> types, then this field should be set
        to the URL of another installation that does provide access for
        that user type (if available).
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Bug Report URL</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        This URL specifies a link that can be used to report bugs. It 
        defaults to the bug tracking system for the &product; development 
        team and shouldn't be changed unless you wish to track bugs 
        separately. 
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>User</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Allow new public users on the system</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        For security reasons, a &product; installation may choose not to
        support <link linkend="public_user">public users</link>.
        Setting this parameter will allow public users to automatically
        generate their own accounts and to use the system immediately.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Allow new member users on the system</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        A &product; installation may be installed purely for use by
        <link linkend="public_user">public users</link>.  
        Typically, such an installation would not be
        associated with an array center and would exist for the purpose
        of sharing and analyzing existing data.  Unsetting this
        parameter will restrict the kinds
        users allowed on such an installation and will help avoid confusion.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>General Inactivity Logout (minutes)</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        This specifies the number of inactive minutes
        before <link linkend="member_user">member users</link> 
        and <link linkend="public_user">public users</link> are
        automatically logged out. 
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Administrator Inactivity Logout (minutes)</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        This specifies the number of inactive minutes
        before <link linkend="administrator_user">administrator users</link> 
        are automatically logged out. 
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Number of days a new public user has to confirm their
        account</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link linkend="public_user">Public users</link> who request
        an account but fail to login within the specified number of
        days
        will be automatically removed from the system.  Public user
        removal is managed automatically, but can also be done manually
        from the <link linkend="remove_inactive_users">Remove Inactive
        Users</link> GUI tool or the <link
        linkend="geoss_rm_inactive_users"><command>geoss_rm_inactive_users</command></link>
        command line tool.  The manual techniques allow removal of all types of
        <link linkend="users">users</link>, not just public users.  
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Allow all users to load data</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        Selecting this option will make the "Load Study Data" link
        appear on <link linkend="user_gui">&mem_home;</link>.  This
        allows users to load all data for one of their studies from a
        file they have previously uploaded.  This option is typically
        enabled on installations not associated with an array center. 
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Array Center</title> 

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Enable Array Center Processing</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        This option should be enabled on installations associated with
        an array center.  It enables the creation or array center staff
        users and enables links in <link
        linkend="array_center_staff_gui">&array_home;</link>
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Array Center Staff Email</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        This is the email address of the <link
        linkend="array_center_staff_user">Array Center Staff User</link>
        who is responsible for fulfilling <link
        linkend="array_order"> array order</link> requests and uploading <link
        linkend="gene_chip_data">gene chip data</link>.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Array Center Staff Inactivity Logout (minutes)</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        This specifies the number of inactive minutes
        before <link linkend="array_center_staff_user">array center
        staff users</link> 
        are automatically logged out. 
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Add array center staff to all groups by default</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        If selected, this will cause new <link
        linkend="array_center_staff_user"> array center staff users 
        </link>  to be added to all <link linkend="group">groups</link>
        when user is added.
        Additionally, when new groups are added, existing array center
        staff users will automatically be added to the group.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Order Number Format</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        This link specifies the convention used to determine the <link
        linkend="order_number">order number</link>.  This number is used
        in naming <link linkend="hybridization">hybridizations</link>
        and consequently the data files loaded by the array center staff
        member.  Year sequential order numbers take the format
        "07-05", where 07 means year 2007 and 05 means the fifth order
        of the year.  Sequential order numbers are generated via
        sequence that does not get reset.  User configurable order
        numbers allow the array center staff user to enter the order
        number.

        <note>The only format that has received extensive testing is
        year sequential.</note>
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Data Publishing</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Enable Data Publishing</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        This option enables the links to publish data and the option on
        the GEOSS home page to view published data.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Public Data Admin Email</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        This is the email address of the <link
        linkend="public_data_administrator">Public Data Administrator</link>
         who will receive emails regarding data that is to be published.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
         
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Analysis</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Enable Analysis Package</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        This option enables the links associated with creating and
        viewing analysis trees.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Configurable Text</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Organization Name</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
This is the name of the organization installing the &product; system. This 
value is used for display purposes only on the home page.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Header/Footer Link Text</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        Each installation has the ability to add a custom
        link to the navigational controls. This is the text
        that will be displayed for that link. 
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Header/Footer Link URL</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        Each installation has the ability to add a custom
        link to the navigational controls. This is the URL
        of the link.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Custom Home Page Description</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        Each installation has the ability to add a custom
        home page description.  This description will appear on the site
        home page prior to the generic &product; description. 
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Custom News Item #1</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        Each installation can configure custom "news items"
        that can be used to inform users of periodic events such as
        training sessions or GEOSS related publications or activities.
        Item #1 will appear just above the <link
        linkend="view_public_data">View Public Data</link> link on the
        home page.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Custom News Item #2</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        Each installation can configure custom "news items"
        that can be used to inform users of periodic events such as
        training sessions or GEOSS related publications or activities.
        Item #2 will appear in the top left hand corner of the home
        page.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="&product;_installation_information">
    <title>&product; Installation Information</title>
    <para>The installation information link provides details about the 
&product; installation on your system. This page is strictly informative 
in nature and may be used to diagnose installation difficulties. It 
reports the build parameters of the system, the installed versions 
of required software, whether the permissions on essential directories 
are correct, the currently loaded layouts, and the currently loaded 
analyses.</para>
   </sect1>

   <sect1 id="change_the_postgres_password_for_the_&product;_user">
     <title>Change the Postgres password for the &product; user</title>
     <para>
For security reasons, the password protecting the geoss database
should be changed periodically.  It is important that both the 
password in Postgres for the geoss user and the password in the 
&product; access file be
changed to the same value.  If only one of these is changed, the
&product; web GUI will be unable to connect to the database.  This link
can be used to simultaneously change both passwords.
     </para>
   </sect1>

   <sect1 id="email_all_users">
     <title>Email all users</title>
     <para>
This link is intended to be used to contact all users of a specific
&product; installation.  Typically, it is used to inform users about
system outages or training sessions.
     </para>
   </sect1>
</article>

<article id="user_administration">
   <title>User Administration</title>
   <sect1 id="view_user_list">
   <title>View user list</title>
   <para>This page provides information regarding all configured users.
   &how_sort;
   </para>
   </sect1>


    <sect1 id="add_a_user">
    <title>Add a user</title>
      <para>
      This page allows the administrator to add a user.  The following
      fields are mandatory:

      <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Login Name</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        This is the user's login name. They will use it to
        log in to &product;.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
         
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Initial Login Password</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        This is the user's password.  They will use it to
        log in to &product; initially. Users should be encouraged
        to change their password after their initial login. 
        &password_rule;
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
         
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Confirm Initial Login Password</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        This must be the same as the Initial Login
        Password.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
         
      <varlistentry>
        <term>User Type</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        This field indicates the type of <link linkend="users">user</link>.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
         
      <varlistentry>
        <term>PI Login:</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        This is login name of the <link 
        linkend="primary_investigator">Primary Investigator
        (PI)</link> associated with the new user. All <link
        linkend="users">users</link> must have
        a PI. A user may be their own PI, as is typically the case with
        <link linkend="administrator_user">administrator users</link>  
        and <link linkend="array_center_staff_user">array center staff
        users</link>. 
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
         
      </variablelist>
      </para>
      <para>Most of the other fields are self-explanatory.  Although
        an email address is not required, it is strongly recommended.
        Email addresses are used to send users notification of their new
        account and to provide information about the processing of
        <link linkend="array_order">array >orders</link> and 
        analysis trees.
      </para>
      <para>There may be a series of select boxes to indicate
        membership in a variety of <link
        linkend="special_center">special centers</link>  These will vary
        based on the special centers configured on your system.  Users
        can be made members of an special center by selecting "Yes".
        Selecting "Administrator" will designate the user as a <link
        linkend="special_center_administrator_user">Special Center
        Administrator User</link> for that special center.
      </para>
      <para>
        Users can also be added using the <link
        linkend="geoss_adduser"><command>geoss_adduser</command></link> command line
        script.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="remove_a_user">
    <title>Remove a user</title>
      <para>
      Typically there should be no need to remove a user. Most users who
      no longer have access to the system will be disabled.
      However, if you have added a user with an incorrect login
      name, you may deleted and re-enter the user. This will
      need to be done before the user uses the account as
      users who own data or who are PIs for other users can not be
      deleted.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="disable_a_user">
    <title>Disable a user</title>
      <para>
      If a <link linkend="users">user</link>should no longer 
      have log in privileges to the system,
      but owns data, they need to be disabled. Once they are
      disabled, they will no longer be able to login. If they
      are currently logged on when they are disabled, they will
      be able to continue to use the system until they logout
      or their session expires.
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="enable_a_user">
    <title>Enable a user</title>
      <para>
      In the event that you need access to a disabled user's
      account, you can re-enable the account. You will need to set 
      <link linkend="users">user</link> type.
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="change_user_password">
    <title>Change user password</title>
      <para>
        The administrator can change the password of any <link
        linkend="users">user</link>. Simply
        select the target user and set the new password. 
        &password_rule;
      </para>
      <para>
        User passwords can be also be changed via the <link
        linkend="geoss_change_userpw"><command>geoss_change_userpw</command></link> command
        line script.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="remove_inactive_users">
    <title>Remove inactive users</title>
      <para>
      This script will remove <link linkend="inactive_user">inactive
      users</link>.  Users are considered
      inactive if they have not logged in for a specified number of
      days.  
      </para>
      <para>Users can also be removed using the
      <link
      linkend="geoss_rm_inactive_users"><command>geoss_rm_inactive_users</command></link>
      command line script.
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="manage_pis_and_users">
    <title>Manage PIs and Users</title>
    <para>All <link linkend="users">users</link> must have at least one
    <link linkend="primary_investigator">PI</link>.  The initial PI for
    a user is set when the user account is created.  However, it is
    possible for users to have more than one PI if they work on multiple
    experiments or for users to change PIs.  This page can be used to
    manage PI/user associations.  To use this page, select the user you
    wish to modify.  You may either add/delete PIs for the user by selecting
    "Edit PIs Associated with this User" or, if the user is a PI, you
    may select "Edit Users Associated with this PI" to modify associated
    users.  You will not be able to make any changes that result in a
    user not having a PI.  For instance, if the user has only one PI,
    you will not be able to remove that PI until a new PI has first been
    added.
    </para>
    <para>Administrative users often do not have a logical PI.  In these
    instances, users should be their own PI.</para>
    </sect1>
</article>

<article id="special_center_administration">
    <title>Special Center Administration</title>
    <sect1 id="view_all_special_centers">
    <title>View all special centers</title>
    <para>
    This page shows all <link linkend="special_center">Special
    Centers</link> configured for the system. &how_sort;
    </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="add_a_special_center">
    <title>Add a special center</title>
    <para>
    This page allows administrators to add a <link
    linkend="special_center">Special Center</link>.  Fields are defined
    below:
    
    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Special Center Name</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        The name of the special center is displayed in numerous
        locations.  Most notably, <link
        linkend="special_center_member">special center members</link>
        can associate their <link linkend="array_order">array orders </link>
        with a special center.  This is done
        by special center name.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Special Center Description</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
         For display purposes only.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Special Center Phone Number</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        For display purposes only.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Billing Discount (%)</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        Centers can receive discounts on <link
        linkend="array_order">array orders</link>.  This shows up
        in the <link linkend="array_center_staff_view_reports">billing
        reports</link>.  At this time, the billing component of
        &product; is still very 
        <link linkend="university_of_virginia">UVa</link> specific
        and there is no way to modify the billing formula.
        </para>
        <para>
        Currently, users are billed for the cost of chips used in their
        order and for array center staff labor.  The discount applies to
        the labor component of the bill.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Special Center URL</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        If the special center has their own website, &product; will link
        to it.  If the special center logo is set to display on the main
        page, then the URL specified here will be linked to the logo.
        Remember to include the "http://".
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Special Center Logo</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        Each special center can have a logo associated with it.  Logos
        files must first be uploaded from <link
        linkend="upload_logo_or_icon_file">Upload logo/icon file</link>
        in &center_home; and can then be associated with the
        special center.  Logos can be displayed on the main page if that
        option is set.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Special Center Icon</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        Eventually, we hope to have an icon associated with special
        centers that will be associated with <link
        linkend="users">users</link> who are members of that special
        center.  Unfortunately, this feature is not implemented yet.
        So, while you can set an icon file, it is not used anywhere.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Display Logo on Main Page</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        If this option is selected and a logo file is configured, then
        it will be displayed on the &product; home page.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Orders Require Approval Before Array Center Processing</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        If this option is selected, when a user submits an <link
        linkend="array_order">array order</link>, an email is sent to the <link
        linkend="special_center_administrator_user">special center
        administrators</link> requesting they approve the order. Once
        the order has been approved, an email is sent to <link
        linkend="array_center_staff_user">array center staff</link>
        informing them that the order is ready for processing.
        </para>
        <para>If this option is not selected, orders associated with the
        special center are automatically approved and sent directly to
        the array center staff upon submission.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
         
    </variablelist>
    </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="delete_a_special_center">
    <title>Delete a special center</title>
    This page can be used to remove a <link
    linkend="special_center">Special Center</link>.  Special Centers can
    only be removed if they have no <link linkend="array_order">
    array orders</link> associated with them.
    This option is mostly intended for removal of special centers that
    have been added erroneously.
    </sect1>
</article>
</part>
