<part id="admin_workflow">
<title>Overview: Workflows for Administrator Users</title>
<article id="&product;_administration_overview">
<title>&product; Administration</title>
<para>The initial responsibility of the administrator is to configure
&product; correctly and ensure the installation is secure. &product;
system parameters should be set during product installation via the
<link linkend="configure_&product;">Configure &product;</link>.  System
status should be verified via the <link
linkend="&product;_installation_information">&product; Installation
Information</link> link.  When the information displayed here is
satisfactory, installation is complete.</para>
<para>There are also links for periodic tasks like changing the Postgres
password for the geoss user and emailing all users.  While these 
tasks can be done
manually, &admin_home; provides an easy mechanism for these periodic
maintenance tasks.</para>

</article>
<article id="user_administration_overview">
<title>User Administration</title>
<para>The primary on-going responsibility for &product; administrators
is <link linkend="users">user</link> administration.  This includes adding, removing, disabling and
enabling users.  Additionally, each user is associated with a <link
linkend="primary_investigator">PI</link> and administrators may need
manage those associations.</para>
<para>
Potential new users can use the <link
linkend="request_an_account">Request An Account</link> link on the 
main page to request an account.  When an account
is requested, the administrator is emailed with all the relevant
information.  The email includes a link to take the administrator
straight to the account creation page and to populate all the fields as
specified by the requester.  Please note that the administrator must
already be logged into &product; to utilize the automatic field
population feature.  Alternatively, administrators can just use the
<link linkend="add_a_user">Add A User</link> and specify information
manually.
</para>
<para>Active users (those who have data on the system) cannot be
removed.  This is because &product; acts as a data repository and data
does not get deleted.  Currently, there isn't a feature to change the
ownership of the data, so it is necessary to maintain users who own
data.  However, if it is necessary to terminate a user's access to the system,
the administrator can disable the user's account.</para>
</article>
<article id="special_center_administration_overview">
<title>Special Center Administration</title>
<para>Administrators are responsible for adding and removing <link
linkend="special_center">Special Centers</link>.  Special Centers are
essentially groups of users that have different needs regarding the
billing and/or processing of their orders.  Administrators use GUI tools
from &admin_home; to add and remove special centers, specify billing
discounts for the special center and to define whether
the Special Center's logo should be displayed on the &product; main page.
The administrator can also use GUI tools from <link
linkend="special_center_gui">&center_home;</link> to edit
members in a special center, upload icons and logos, and to view reports
for the center.  The tools in &center_home; are intended for use by <link
linkend="special_center_administrator_user">Special Center Administrator
Users</link>, who can perform a subset of the actions available to
&product; administrators.</para>
</article>

<article id="bulk_data_configuration">
<title>Bulk Data Configuration</title>
<para>
This article describes the mechanism for configuring and loading data
from the command line.  This process is useful for importing large
amounts of data (historical data) and importing data from other systems.  
</para>
<para>
The basic process for loading from the command line is:
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
Assemble and format data files for loading
</listitem>
<listitem>
Verify correct data dependencies, including adding users with
<link linkend="geoss_bulk_adduser"><command>geoss_bulk_adduser</command></link>
</listitem>
<listitem>
Test data configuration and run the configurator
</listitem>
<listitem>
Run the bulk loader
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
Each step is discussed below in detail.
</para>

<formalpara>
<title>Compile data files into appropriate path structure</title>
<para>
The first step in this process is to compile all the data you wish to
load.  Data files should be put in a special directory structure.  The
top level directory should contain subdirectories that correspond to the
<link linkend="&product;_login_id">&product;_login_id</link> of the user
who owns the data to be loaded.  Inside each user directory, there
should be one directory for each <link linkend="array_study">array
study</link> to be loaded.  Each study directory contains the a series
of files relating to the study configuration and one or more files
specifying data.  See the documentation for <link linkend=
"geoss_bulk_configurator"><command>geoss_bulk_configurator</command></link>
for details on the required directory structure.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Configure data dependencies</title>
Once you have the appropriate data directory ready for load, you should
ensure that all data dependencies are satisfied.
When you load data for studies and orders, that data often references
data from other tables (via the primary key).  In order for the
configuration to work successfully, all data that is linked to must be
configured.  Specifically, you should verify that the user who owns the
data exists, the correct species exist, and the correct arraylayouts
exist.  Additionally, if you are configuring associated diseases or
special centers they will need to exist as well.  Note that running the
bulk configurator with the --readonly flag will allow you to check many
of these errors.
</formalpara>

<para>
There are  command-line utilites to facilitate the creation of users:
<link linkend="geoss_bulk_adduser"><command>geoss_bulk_adduser</command></link>,
and <link linkend="geoss_adduser"><command>geoss_adduser</command></link>.
There is a command-line utility to facilitate creation of layouts:
<link linkend="geoss_loadaffylayout"><command>geoss_loadaffylayout
</command></link>,
Species and diseases are loaded directly into the db when the
<link linkend="geoss_initialize">geoss_initialize</link> command is run.
If you need to add additional species or disease, do so directly through
the psql command line tool.
</para>

<formalpara>
<title>Test data configuration and run the configurator</title>
When data dependencies are resolved, it is time to run
<command>geoss_bulk_configurator</command>.  This script will create
studies based on the input data path passed to it as a
parameter.  It is advisable to initially run the script in readonly mode
to verify correct configuration of data.  If the create sequence from
the readonly output looks acceptable, and no errors are reported, rerun
the script without the readonly flag to correctly load data.
</formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Run the bulk loader</title>
After running <command>geoss_bulk_configurator</command> successfully,
studies and orders have been created, but the are not loaded.  To
actually load the data, run <link linkend="geoss_bulk_load">
<command>geoss_bulk_load</command></link> to load by study or <link
linkend="geoss_load_available"><command>geoss_load_available</command>
</link> to load by order.  Once this is complete, the entire bulk load 
process is complete.
</formalpara>

</article>
</part>
