<article id="admin_faq" class="faq">
<title>Administrator FAQ</title>

<qandaset>
<qandadiv id="admin_faq_administrator_account"><title>Administrator Account</title></qandadiv>

<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
     How do I log in as <link linkend="administrator_user">administrator</link>?
    </para>
  </question> 
  <answer>
    <para>
     Logging in as an administrator is the same as logging in as a regular 
     user. Provide your <link linkend="&product;_login_id">login</link> and 
     password in the login section of the &product; home page.
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry> 

<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
    How do I change the <link linkend="administrator_user">administrator</link>    password?
    </para>
  </question> 
  <answer>
    <para>
     Administrators can change their password in two ways. They can log 
     on and change their password via the 
     <link linkend="change_user_password">Change User Password</link> 
     link from <link linkend="admin_gui">&admin_home;</link> 
     or through the 
     <link linkend="change_my_password">Change My Password</link> 
     link from <link linkend="user_gui">&mem_home;</link> 
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry> 

        
<qandadiv id="admin_faq_user_administration"><title>User Administration</title></qandadiv>
        
<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
    Why can't I remove a <link linkend="users">user</link>?
    </para>
  </question> 
  <answer>
    <para>
    If the user owns any data, you will not be able to remove them. If this 
    is the case, their <link linkend="&product;_login_id">login</link> 
    won't even show up in the drop down list for users that you are allowed 
    to remove. 
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry> 

<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
    How do I change a <link linkend="users">user's</link> password?
    </para>
  </question> 
  <answer>
    <para>
          User <link linkend="password">passwords</link> can be changed 
          via the <link linkend="change_user_password">Change User
          Password</link> in <link linkend="admin_gui">&admin_home;</link>. 
          Passwords can also be changed using the <link
          linkend="geoss_change_userpw"><command>geoss_change_userpw</command></link>
           command line script.
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry> 

<qandadiv id="admin_faq_layout_management"><title>Layout Management</title></qandadiv>
        
<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
    Where do I get <link linkend="layout">layouts</link>?
    </para>
  </question> 
  <answer>
    <para>
      Layouts can be obtained from the <ulink
      url="http://www.affymetrix.com/support/technical/byproduct.affx?cat=arrays">Affymetrix
      website</ulink>.
      Click on the hyperlink for the array of interest and scroll down 
      to the section "NetAffx Annotation Files." Choose the 
      .CSV file.  This file will contain more columns than are needed 
      for our system.  Eliminate all columns with the exception of 
      GeneChip Array, Probe Set ID, Representative Public ID, Sequence Type,
      and Target Description. Columns should be in this order.
      Save file as a text file making sure that the first row is actual 
      data. To do so remove column headings from the text file. 
    </para>
    <para>
      For convenience, we supply the layouts we use in a file,
       <filename>geoss_layouts.tar.gz</filename>, that
      is available for download from the &sourceforge_site;.  Generally,
      these should be downloaded as part of the installation process.
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry> 


<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
     How do I load a <link linkend="layout">layout</link>?
    </para>
  </question> 
  <answer>
    <para>
    Layouts should be in text format for loading. Currently you 
    must run the <link
    linkref="geoss_loadaffylayout"><command>geoss_loadaffylayout</command></link> 
    script from the command line. 
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry> 


<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
    How do I unload a <link linkend="layout">layout</link>?
    </para>
  </question> 
  <answer>
    <para>
    Affymetrix layouts are loaded into three tables in the following 
    order: <database class="table">arraylayout</database>,
    <database class="table">al_spots</database> and 
    <database class="table">usersequencefeature</database>. The only 
    way to remove a layout is to do so manually. You must identify all 
    the fields first and then delete in reverse order or the foreign 
    key constraints will not allow the deletion. The <database
    class="table">arraylayout</database>table 
    will have only one record, however, the <database
    class="table">al_spots</database> and <database
    class="table">usersequencefeature</database> 
    tables will have many. Identify the records by associating 
    the foreign key relationships and then begin your delete. As always 
    it is a good idea to have a backup (<command>pg_dump</command>)
     done just in case.
    <note>
    Removing layouts should not typically be required. 
    </note>
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry> 

<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
    Why can't I unload a <link linkend="layout">layout?</link> 
    </para>
  </question> 
  <answer>
    <para>
    Most likely you are attempting to remove a layout from the arraylayout 
    table before deleting the associated records in the <database
    class="table">usersequencefeature</database>
    and <database class="table">al_spots</database> tables. 
    You must do the deletes in the reverse order 
    from which the tables are populated. The foreign key 
    constraints will keep you from leaving orphan records in any child 
    tables.
    </para>
    <para>
    Another possibility is that you are attempting to delete a layout 
    that has already been associated with some data.  Layouts should
    not be deleted if they have associated data. 
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry> 

<qandadiv id="admin_faq_analysis_management"><title>Analysis Management</title></qandadiv>
        
<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
    Where do I get <link linkend="analysis">analyses</link>?
    </para>
  </question> 
  <answer>
    <para>
    Analyses are developed by &product; developers and loaded into
    &product; during the install. 
    As new analyses are created, 
    they will be included in system updates. It is possible to write your 
    own analyses, but you will need to have &product; source installed to do 
    this. If you have an analysis you would like to have included in
    &product;, please contact the <link
    linkend="&product;_developers">GEOSS developers</link>.
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry> 

<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
    How can I load an <link linkend="analysis">analysis</link>? 
    </para>
  </question> 
  <answer>
    <para>
    Analyses are loaded via the <link
    linkend="geoss_add_analysis"><command>geoss_add_analysis</command></link> 
    command.
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry> 

<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
    How can I unload an <link linkend="analysis">analysis</link>? 
    </para>
  </question> 
  <answer>
    <para>
    Analyses that are not currently in use can be removed using the
    <link linkend="geoss_rm_analysis"><command>geoss_rm_analysis</command>
    </link> 
    command. <note>Typically, you should not need to remove analyses.
    This functionality is generally only required by application
    developers.</note>
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry> 

<qandadiv id="admin_faq_public_data_management"><title>Public Data Management</title></qandadiv>
          
<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
    What is the <link linkend="administrator_user">administrator's</link> 
    role in making publishing <link linkend="public_data">
     public data</link>? 
    </para>
  </question> 
  <answer>
    <para>
    <link linkend="users">Users</link> may choose to make their data 
    available to the public by <link
    linkend="publishing_your_data">publishing their data</link>.  When a
    request to publish is submitted the <link
    linkend="public_data_administrator">Public Data Administrator</link>
    is emailed.  Typically, the Public Data Administrator is the same
    person as the Administrator.
    </para>
    <para>
    The Public Data Administrator reviews the publishing request.
    This is because it may not be the <link
    linkend="primary_investigator">PI</link>
    who submits the request. In that case, the PI is emailed 
    by GEOSS, informing them that their data is about to be published. If 
    they do not wish it to be published, they can contact the 
    Public Data Administrator who can prevent the publication of the 
    data.  When the  Public Data Administrator is satisfied 
    regarding the legitimacy of the request, they post the data on the
    system through a process described in the email they receive.
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry> 

<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
    How do I remove public data? 
    </para>
  </question> 
  <answer>
    <para>
    If data is published that you wish to remove from the site, it can be 
    removed by removing the appropriate files from the public data directory. 
    To determine the public data directory, check the <link
    linkend="&product;_installation_information">GEOSS Installation
     Information</link> 
    link from <link linkend="admin_gui">&admin_home;</link>. 
    Public data is in WEB_DIR/site/public_files. 
    You will need to find the directory named after the PI of the data you 
    wish to remove. If the PI has only published one set of data, you may 
    remove the entire directory. If the PI has published more than one set 
    of data, you will need to remove the appropriate files from inside the 
    directory.  The filenames will include the miame name of the data.
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry> 

</qandaset>
</article>
