<part id="array_center_staff_workflow">
<title>Overview: Workflows for Array Center Staff Users</title>
<article id="processing_orders">
<title>Processing Orders</title>
  <sect1 id="fulfilling_order_requests">
  <title>Fulfilling order requests</title>
    <para>
    When a <link linkend="users">user</link> wants to place an <link 
    linkend="array_order">array order</link>, they will submit an 
    order to the array center.  Array center staff will receive an email
    stating that the order has been submitted.  At this time, array
    center staff can assign an <link linkend="order_number">order 
    number</link> to the order via the <link
    linkend="assign_a_new_order_number">Assign a New
    Order Number</link> or by clicking on the link in the notification
    email. Note that the 
    array center staff user must already be logged in to &product; for 
    the link to work.
    </para>
    <para>
    Typically, orders are created when the user submits an order, and
    the array center staff will assign an order number to the order
    using the "Assign a New Order Number" link.  However, in rare
    circumstances, array center staff may wish to create an order, which
    can be done via the <link linkend="create_a_new_array_order">
    Create a New Array Order</link> link.  Typically, this is done if
    the array center staff wished to reserve an order number for some
    reason.  Orders created in this fashion will have no <link
    linkend="sample">samples</link> associated with them.  These orders
    can later be assigned to a samples via the <link
    linkend="assign_a_historical_order_to_an_existing_study">Assign a
    Historical Order to an Existing Study</link> link. 
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="loading_data">
  <title>Loading data</title>
  <para>
   Once the array center staff has completed running the experiment, the 
   <link linkend="gene_chip_data">gene chip data</link> must be loaded.
   To load the data, the <link linkend="chip_data_files">chip data files
   </link> must be placed in the <link linkend="chip_data_path">chip data
   path</link>.  Not all chip data files are mandatory, but the "txt" 
   file is required and the "rpt" file is recommended.  Other files
   should be loaded so that they are available to the user, but are 
   not mandatory for data load.
  </para>
  <para>
   Once the data files are in place, data must be loaded via the 
   <link linkend="get_one_array_order">Get One Array Order</link> 
   link.
  </para> 
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="billing_and_reports">
  <title>Billing and reports</title>
    <para>
      Several <link linkend="array_center_staff_view_reports">reports
      </link> are available to help the array center staff with their
      billing activities.  This portion of the application has been 
      tailored to the needs of the <link linkend="array_center">array 
      center</link> at the <ulink url="http://www.virginia.edu">UVa</ulink>.
      If your array center requires different functionality, please
      submit an enhancement bug in 
      <ulink url="http://biostat.virginia.edu/bugzilla">our bug tracking 
      system</ulink> and we will try to accommodate your needs.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</article>
</part>
