<glossary id="glossary"><title>&product; Glossary</title>
<para>
</para>

<glossdiv><title>A</title>

<glossentry id="administrator_user">
<glossterm>
Administrator User
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para> The Administrator User oversees the entire
  system. He/she will maintain configuration parameters, manage user
  accounts, and maintain general operation of the system.  </para>
  <glossseealso otherterm="users">Users</glossseealso>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="analysis_condition">
<glossterm>
Analysis Condition
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>Analysis conditions are used to analyze data using <link
  linkend="analysis_tree">analysis trees</link>.  Most analyses compare 
  one or more conditions.  An analysis condition contains data for at least one 
  or more gene chips.  When a condition contains more than one <link 
  linkend="chip">chip</link>, 
  the chips should be generally biological or technical replicates.  Most analysis 
  conditions correspond directly to an <link
  linkend="experiment_condition">experimental condition</link> and are 
  typically created automatically when a user creates an analysis tree 
  for a specific <link linkend="array_study">study</link>.  However, 
    <link linkend="users">users</link> may create their own analysis 
  conditions.  This is useful when grouping data in a non-default 
  configuration or for grouping user uploaded data (as such data does 
  not belong to a study).</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="analysis_files"><glossterm>
  Analysis Files</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  There are many kinds of files involved in running <link
  linkend="analysis">analyses</link> using <link
  linkend="analysis_tree">analysis trees</link>.  These files are
  called analysis files.  They include an input file that contains
  relevant chip data in a specific format, intermediate data files that
  pass data from one analysis to another, and result files that contain
  the results of each analysis module.  Data on the interpretation of
  analysis result files are included in the help for each analysis. 
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="analysis_set">
<glossterm>
Analysis Set
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>Analysis sets are used to analyze data using 
  <link linkend="analysis_tree">analysis trees</link>.  An analysis set 
  should consist of one or more 
  <link linkend="analysis_condition">analysis conditions</link>.  
  Most analysis sets are created automatically when a user creates an 
  analysis tree.  If the user specifies a specific 
  <link linkend="array_study">array study</link> as input, the analysis set 
   will be created with the analysis conditions corresponding 
  to the <link linkend="experiment_condition">experimental conditions</link>
   associated with the study.  <link linkend="users">Users</link> can 
   create their own analysis sets.  This is useful when grouping data 
   in a non-default configuration or for grouping user uploaded data (as 
   such data does not belong to a study).</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="array_center">
<glossterm>
Array Center
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>The center or facility in charge of ordering chips and  performing  
microarray gene 
  expression experiments.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="array_center_staff_user">
<glossterm>Array Center Staff User</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>The Array Center Staff User is responsible for performing 
  microarray
  experiments. This type of user will manage orders, hybridize chips,
  collect and upload chip data to the &product; system, and bill
  for services as appropriate.</para>
  <glossseealso otherterm="users">Users</glossseealso>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="analysis">
<glossterm>
Analysis or Analysis Module
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>

An analysis (module) is an analysis unit that performs a certain analysis function
based on an input data set; it also typically  produces one or more output
data files for interpretation and/or for the use of other connecting analysis modules. 
Typical analysis modules perform statistical calculations, functional/annotational analysis,
 and formatting data.
Analysis modules can be written in many languages, as long as they can
be successfully run from the command line on a Linux system. New analysis modules must be 
added by an <link linkend="administrator_user">administrator user</link>. 
Current analyses are written
in Perl and R. If the output from one analysis can be used as input to
another analysis, they can be chained together in a tree.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>


<glossentry id="analysis_tree">
<glossterm>
Analysis Tree
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>An analysis tree corresponds to an integrated scheme of data analysis
  designed by each user.  
  Each tree requires input, produces output, and performs a variety of 
  calculations and analyses on the input data based on the nodes of analysis modules 
  constructed in the tree.  Each node can be chosen and defined from any   
  <link linkend="analysis">analysis</link> modules</para> compatible with connecting nodes. 
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="array_order">
<glossterm>
Array Order
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para> A request for an array order is initiated by a &product; 
  <link linkend="member_user">member user</link> and submitted to the 
  <link linkend="array_center_staff_user">array center
  staff user</link> for processing. It consists of a request to have 
  <link linkend="sample">samples</link>
  hybridized to <link linkend="chip">gene chips</link>. The array 
  center staff user generates the array order for the member user 
  and then follows through with the
  work request once the member user has supplied all required information
  pertaining to the request.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="array_study">
<glossterm>
Array Study
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>Defined by the <link linkend="member_user">member user</link>,
  an array study is a way of defining and describing a project being
  worked on by a particular member user and/or his/her <link linkend="group">
  group</link>.  An array study is the main logical entity that can hold all <link
  linkend="experiment_condition">experimental conditions</link> under a coherent
  study theme.
  More than one <link linkend="array_order">array order</link> can be
  associated with a single array study.  Additionally, you can add new
  experimental conditions to an array study as time passed. 
 </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>


</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>B</title>

<glossentry id="biological_replicate">
<glossterm>
Biological Replicate
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
Biological Replicates are different biological subjects under a same
experimental or treatment condition that can show individual sampling
variability of the target population.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>C</title>

<glossentry id="categorical_parameter">
<glossterm>
Categorical Parameter
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  A type of parameter used by <link linkend="criteria_file">criteria
  files</link>.  A categorical parameter is a categorization that has a
  finite number of distinct options.  An example of such a parameter is
  gender, which has two levels of option "male" and "female".
  </para>
  <glossseealso otherterm="continuous_parameter">Continuous Parameter</glossseealso>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="cdna">
<glossterm>
cDNA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>cDNA (complementary DNA) is DNA that is reverse-transcribed from an mRNA
  template.  cDNA microarrays are one of widely-used microarray technologies for measuring
  gene expression. Currently, &product; does not support the data analysis from this
  platform; this support is planned to be developed in 2005.  &product; currently supports
  the Affymetrix <productname
  class="registered">GeneChip</productname> data.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="chip">
<glossterm>
Chip
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  A small (a few centimeters on each side) glass or other solid surface
  on which thousands of immobilized oligonucleotide probes (or cDNA clones) have been
  synthesized or robotically deposited in a predetermined array, so that
  automated recording of fluorescence from each of the positions may be
  easily determined.  Also called an array, an array, or a
  microarray.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="chip_cost">
<glossterm>
Chip Cost
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>Each <link linkend="chip">chip</link> has a cost associated with
  it.  The price is set when the <link linkend="layout">layout</link> is
  added and cannot be modified except through direct interaction with
  the database.  The chip cost is used in calculating the bill for an
  <link linkend="array_order"> array order</link>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="chip_data_files">
<glossterm>
Chip Data Files
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>When the <link linkend="array_center_staff_user">array center 
  staff user</link> runs the array experiment the results are stored in chip
  data files.  Once the array center staff user loads the data, these 
  files are available for download.  File formats may include: 
    
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
    <term>
    cel 
    </term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    CEL files contain intensity values of all individual (perfect-match 
    and mis-match) probes on an array
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
    <term>
    dat 
    </term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    an chip image file including information on pixel intensities, grid
    coordinates, and scan parameters
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
    <term>
    chp 
    </term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    the CHP file contains the analysis results with one summary intensity
    value for each probe set from the probe pairs on the set (by Tukey's
    bi-weight statistics); this file can be obtained by  the GeneChip
    Operating Software, GCOS 1.0 (January `05)
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
    <term>
    exp 
    </term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    The EXP file contains experiment information as captured by
    GCOS
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
    <term>
    txt 
    </term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    data file containing probe set signals (equivalent to CHP file)
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
    <term>
    cab 
    </term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    a compilation of some of the other files generated by GCOS
    software
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="chip_data_path">
<glossterm>
Chip Data Path
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  This is the initial location (actual or parent directory) of the 
  <link linkend="chip_data_files">chip data files.</link>  The <link
  linkend="array_center_staff_user">array center staff</link> places
  data files in this directory (or a subdirectory of this directory)
  prior to loading data.  The <link
  linkend="administrator_user">&product; administrator</link> must agree
  on this path with the array center staff and set the "Chip Data Path"
  field in the <link linkend="configure_&product;">Configure
  &product;</link> accordingly.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="chip_name">
<glossterm>
Chip Name
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  Each type of <link linkend="chip">chip</link> has an associated name 
  that is set by the <link linkend="administrator_user">administrator 
  user</link> when the <link linkend="layout">layout</link> for that
  chip is loaded.  If the chip is an Affymetrix 
  <productname class="registered">GeneChip</productname>, the 
  &product; name must 
  correspond to the name specified in the rpt file (under "Probe Array 
  Type") for data to load correctly.  Otherwise a chip type mismatch 
  error is detected.  Administrators may specify additional information 
  about the chip in parenthesis behind the chip name
  if necessary.  
  </para>
  <para>
  For example, the Affymetrix name for the P.Aeruginoas chip is
  "Pae_G1a".  The &product; name is "Pae_G1a (p.aeruginoas)."</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="chip_replicate">
<glossterm>
Chip Replicate
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
Chip replicates are the technically replicated arrays (or replicated hybridizations)
with the same RNA samples.
This kind of replication is useful to identify many false positives in microarray data analysis. 
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="companion_installation">
<glossterm>
Companion Installation
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  Installations that support an <link
  linkend="array_center">array center</link> may not wish to allow
  public accounts on that installation.  As public accounts can be
  created automatically and public users can upload files and run <link
  linkend="analysis">analyses</link> there are security implications to
  having public user accounts.  For this reason, a companion
  installation can be specified in the
  <link linkend="configure_&product;">&product;
  Configuration</link>.  Companion installations should be completely
  separate installations (on different hardware) that support
  complementary <link linkend="users">user types</link>.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="continuous_parameter">
<glossterm>
Continuous Parameter
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  A type of parameter used by <link linkend="criteria_file">criteria
  files</link>.  A continuous parameter is a categorization that has a
  range of options.  Grouping based on continuous parameters tends to
  use less than and greater than operators.  An example of such a
   parameter is age.  Grouping could occur based on age ranges.
  </para>
  <glossseealso otherterm="categorical_parameter">Categorical Parameter</glossseealso>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="criteria_file"><glossterm>
  Criteria File</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  A criteria file is a file uploaded by the user that defines
  associations between their data.  The criteria file can be used (via
  the <link linkend="create_new_analysis_condition">Create new analysis
  condition</link> and the <link
  linkend="create_new_set_of_conditions">Create new set of conditions</link>
  links) to create <link linkend="analysis_condition">analysis
  conditions</link>  and <link linkend="analysis_set">analysis
  sets</link> based on specific criteria.  For instance, the criteria
  file might contain gender information for all of your <link
  linkend="hybridization">hybridizations</link>.  You could then create
  an analysis condition that contained all data associated with females
  and an analysis condition for all data associated with males.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>D</title>

<glossentry id="default_public_user">
<glossterm>
Default Public User
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
This user is created by default by the <link
linkend="geoss_initialize">geoss_initialize</link> script.  The default
public user is a special user in that all users are a part of the public
group.  This means that data sets loaded for the default public user is
accessible to all.  This is intended for use in loading external data
sets that other users may wish to analyze.
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>
</glossdiv>


<glossdiv><title>E</title>

<glossentry id="experiment_condition">
<glossterm>
Experiment Condition
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para><link linkend="array_study">Studies</link> consist of one or more 
  experiment conditions.  An experiment condition is the group
  of chips under the same experimental/treatment condition in a 
  microarray study.  (add example)</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>G</title>

<glossentry id="gcos">
<glossterm>
GeneChip Operating Software
</glossterm>
<accronym>GCOS</accronym>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  GCOS is freely available <ulink url="http://www.affymetrix.com/">
  Affymetrix</ulink> software used for working with its GeneChip data.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="&product;">
<glossterm>
Gene Expression Open Source System
</glossterm>
<accronym>&product;</accronym>
<glossdef>
  <para>&product; is a web-based tool for the storage an analysis of 
  <link linkend="gene_chip_data">gene chip data</link>.
    For a detailed description of the software see <link 
  linkend="introduction_to_&product;">Introduction to &product;</link></para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="&product;_access_file">
<glossterm>
&product; Access File
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  This file contains the password for the <link linkend="postgres_user">
  Postgres User</link> and allows the web application to access the
  database.  The file is readable only by the Linux user who
  runs the web server.  To determine the location of the file, check the
  value for WEB_DIR under the <link
  linkend="&product;_installation_information">&product; Installation
  Information</link> link.  The file is located in the directory shown 
  there and has the
  filename <filename>.geoss</filename>.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>


<glossentry id="&product;_login_id">
<glossterm>
&product; Login Id
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>This is the unique identifier for a &product; user.  All 
  <link linkend="users">users</link> have a &product; login id and 
  use it to login to the system. The id is selected by the 
  <link linkend="administrator_user"> administrator</link> when 
  the user account is created and is typically a 
  short combination of letters and numbers.  
</para>
<note>
<para>
<link linkend="public_user">Public users</link> select their own 
&product; login id unless it already exists in the system.
</para>
</note>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gene_chip_data">
<glossterm>
Gene Chip Data
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  Gene chip data describes the results of a gene chip experiment and contains 
  information like signal intensity values.  When the <link 
  linkend="array_center_staff_user"> array center staff user </link> loads
  the gene chip data, &product; stores it both in the database and in 
  file format.  <link linkend="member_user"> Member users </link> can 
  download files from the <link linkend="view_my_files"> View My Files </link>
  link.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="genex">
<glossterm>
GeneX
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>GeneX is the name of the original open source software that &product; is based
  on.  See <ulink url="http://genex.sourceforge.net/">GeneX 2</ulink> for
  current information on GeneX.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="genex-va">
<glossterm>
GeneX-Va
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>GeneX-Va is the former name of &product;. </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="group">
<glossterm>
Group
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>In &product;, each user has at least one group, and can define 
  multiple groups, under which different 
  <link linkend="users">users</link> can be added with 
  different access privileges (read or write) to specific array studies and data. 
 Only the user who owns the full control on them, typically Principal Investigator (PI) user,
 can manipulate this group creation and access options.  
  Users can belong to more than one group and users may own more 
  than one group.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>


</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>H</title>
<glossentry id="hybridization">
<glossterm>
Hybridization
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>In &product;, "hybridization" refers to a 
    <link linkend="gene_chip_data"> gene chip or array</link> that
    corresponds to a specific hybridization of a sample.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>I</title>
<glossentry id="inactive_user">
<glossterm>
Inactive User
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  An inactive user is a user who has an account but has never logged in.
  In order to be considered inactive, a configurable number of days must
  have passed since the account was created.  To determine the number of
  days on a given installation, check the "Number of days a new public
  user has to confirm their account" parameter under the <link
  linkend="configure_&product;">Configure &product;</link> link in <link
  linkend="admin_gui">&admin_home;</link>.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>L</title>
<glossentry id="layout">
<glossterm>
Layout
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
A layout is information pertaining to an Affymetrix 
<productname class="registered">GeneChip</productname>
probe array. The layout information describes which probes
belong to probe sets on the array. Currently &product; only supports layouts
for the Affymetrix technology.  However, work is under way
to incorporate <link linkend="cdna">cDNA</link> data and its associated layouts.
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="login">
<glossterm>Login</glossterm>
<glosssee otherterm="&product;_login_id"/>
</glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>M</title>

<glossentry id="microarray_suite">
<glossterm>
Microarray Suite
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>Microarray Suite Software (MAS) is an Affymetrix product used
  for <link linkend="chip">GeneChip</link> 
    data analysis, which is recently replaced by the GCOS software.  
   See <ulink url=
  "http://www.affymetrix.com/products/sofware/specific/mas.affx">
  the Affymetrix specification</ulink> for further information.  
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>


<glossentry id="miame">
<glossterm>
MIAME
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para><ulink url="http://www.mged.org/Workgroups/MIAME/miame.html">Minimum
  Information About A Microarray Experiment (MIAME)</ulink>
  data describes information that is
  needed to enable the interpretation of the results of the experiment
  unambiguously and potentially to reproduce the experiment.
   MIAME is the current standard of microarray information defined 
  by the international Microarray Gene Expression Data Society (MGED). 
</para>
<para>
&product; is working towards MIAME compliance.  Although
researchers are not required to enter MIAME information, 
they are encouraged to provide MIAME
information, particularly when 
<link linkend="publishing_your_data">publishing study data</link> as 
it increases the
usability of the study data.
</para>

</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="member_user">
<glossterm>
Member User
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>A member user is a <link linkend="users">user</link>
   who has access to array lab functionality, particularly 
   placing <link linkend="array_order">array orders</link>.  
   Due to increased access, the identity of member users must be
   confirmed prior to creation of their accounts.
  </para>
  <glossseealso otherterm="users">Users</glossseealso>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

</glossdiv>


<glossdiv><title>O</title>

<glossentry id="order_number">
<glossterm>
Order Number
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>Each <link linkend="array_order">array order</link> has an 
  associated order number that is created when  the
  <link linkend="array_center_staff_user"> array center staff user</link>
  responds to an array order request.  The numbering sequence was 
  designed to meet the needs of the UVa array center.
  &order_number_rule;
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="order_status">
<glossterm>
Order Status
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>Each <link linkend="array_order">array order</link> has an 
  associated order status.  The status can be:
  <variablelist>
 
  
  <varlistentry>
  <term>
    Incomplete
  </term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Array order has been generated, but is not configured in a valid
    way.  &valid_order_config_rule;
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry>
  <term>
     Complete
  </term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
  Array order has been generated and as a valid configuration.
  The order has not yet been submitted to the <link
  linkend="array_center">array center</link> to inform them 
  that it is ready for processing.  Submitted Array order has 
  been submitted to the array center or to the <link
  linkend="special_center_administrator_user">special
  center administrator</link> as appropriate.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
  <term>
     Approved
  </term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
  The array order has been submitted and it has been approved.  
  Note that many orders receive automatic approval.  Only
  array orders that are associated with a <link
  linkend="special_center">special center</link> that require 
  manual approval do not receive automatic approval.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
  <term>
    Finished
  </term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
  The array center has processed the order and loaded the <link
  linkend="chip_data_files">gene chip data files</link>.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>P</title>

<glossentry id="password">
<glossterm>
Password
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>&password_rule;</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="postgres_database">
<glossterm>
Postgres Database
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>&product; store information in a Postgres database.  If
  &product; is installed via an rpm install and following instructions
  for a generic install, then the name of the database will be "geoss".
  However, it is possible to install with a different database name,
  as may be the case with a developer installation.  To confirm the
  name of the database that your &product; connects to, you can check
  the value of the DB_NAME setting under the <link
  linkend="&product;_installation_information">&product; Installation
  Information</link> link, if you have <link
  linkend="administrator_user">administrator access.</link></para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="postgres_user">
<glossterm>
Postgres User
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>When we refer to the Postgres User, we mean the user defined in
  Postgres (as opposed to a &product; user or a Linux user) 
  that has access to the <link
  linkend="postgres_database">Postgres Database</link>.  To confirm the
  name of the user that your installation uses to connect to the
  Postgres Database, you can check the value of the GEOSS_SU_USER
  setting under the <link
  linkend="&product;_installation_information">&product; Installation
  Information</link> link, if you have 
  <link
  linkend="administrator_user">administrator access.</link>
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="primary_investigator">
<glossterm>
Primary (or Principal) Investigator
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>The primary (or principal) investigator (PI) is a <link
  linkend="member_user">member user</link> who owns studies and their
  associated data.  Every user must be associated with a PI (or several PIs), although the user can be
  PI and choose himself as PI.  A typical setup involves a group with a PI, and several
  staff members.  Staff members often <link
  linkend="placing_an_order_with_the_array_center">define studies and
  orders</link> and perform the majority of the interaction with
  &product;, but the data is still owned by the PI.</para>
  <para>
  If a PI has several different <link
  linkend="array_study">studies</link> and would like to set up
  different access privileges on each one, then the PI should create 
  several <link linkend="group">groups</link> using the <link
  linkend="create_a_new_group">Create a New Group</link> link.  Study
  permissions can then be set so that only members of a specific group
  can see the study using the <link
  linkend="change_permissions_for_array_studies">Change
  group ownership and read/write permissions for existing array
  studies</link> link.  Similarly, permissions for <link
  linkend="array_order">array orders</link>
  can be changed using the <link
  linkend="change_permissions_for_array_orders">Change
  group ownership and read/write permissions for existing array orders
  </link> link.
  </para>
  <para>
  Each <link linkend="users">user</link> is assigned a PI when their
  account is created.  Only the <link
  linkend="administrator_user">Administrator</link> can change these
  associations, which is done using the <link
  linkend="manage_pis_and_users">Manage PIs and Users</link> link from 
  <link linkend="admin_gui">&admin_home;</link>.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="public_data">
<glossterm>
Public Data
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  Once a researcher has published their experiment results, they may
  wish to make the data available to the public. To do this, they enter
  relevant <link linkend="miame">MIAME</link>information about the 
  experiment and then request 
  <link linkend="publishing_your_data">study publication</link>.
  Once published, data is available to all through the
  <link linkend="view_public_data">View Public Data</link> link from
  the &product; home page.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="public_data_administrator">
<glossterm>
Public Data Administrator
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>The Public Data Administrator is responsible for managing 
  the publication of data.  Once a <link linkend="users">user</link> 
  requests publication of experiment results, the public data 
  administrator confirms publication details and makes the appropriate
  files available.
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="public_user">
<glossterm>
Public User
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>Public users have a subset of the functionality of 
  <link linkend="member_user">Member Users</link>.
  They can upload data and perform analyses, but they do not have
  access to array center functionality (placing 
  <link linkend="array_order">array orders</link>).  As
  they do not need to have this kind of access, the identity of 
  a public user does not need to be verified and they are
  able to <link linkend="request_an_account">create their own 
  accounts</link>.
</para>
  <glossseealso otherterm="users">Users</glossseealso>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

</glossdiv>


<glossdiv><title>S</title>

<glossentry id="sample">
<glossterm>
Sample
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>Each <link linkend="array_order">array order</link> must have 
  one or more samples associated with it.  Each sample must be 
  associated with an <link linkend="experiment_condition">
  experimental condition</link>.  A sample can be hybridized into 
  more than one chip.</para>
  <para>
  Sometimes there is a one-to-one correlation between experimental
  conditions and samples, but there can be many samples associated with
  the same experimental condition if the experiment design includes
  biological replicates.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="special_center">
<glossterm>
Special Center
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
    A special center is an entity that has different billing or 
    array processing needs than regular 
    <link linkend="users">users</link>.  Users can be associated
    with multiple special centers, but 
    <link linkend="array_order">array orders</link> may only be 
    associated with one special center.</para>
   <para>
   For an overview of functionality available to special centers, 
   see the <link linkend="special_center_administrator_guide">Special
   Center Administrator Guide</link>.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="special_center_administrator_user">
<glossterm>
Special Center Administrator User
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  <link linkend="users">Users </link> can be designated as a 
  special center administrator.  Special center administrators
  update center information, manage center members, and 
  approve <link linkend="array_order">array orders</link>
   associated with the special center.
  </para>
   <para>
   For an overview of functionality available to special centers, 
   see the <link linkend="special_center_administrator_guide">Special 
   Center Administrator Guide</link>.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="special_center_member">
<glossterm>
Special Center Member
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  A special center member is a <link linkend="users">user</link> who 
  is associated with a <link linkend="special_center">special 
  center</link>.  Special center members can choose to associate
  their <link linkend="array_order">array orders</link> with 
  the special center at the time of order creation.  This may 
  result in billing discounts or in the array order being routed
  through an approval process, depending on the configuration of 
  the special center.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="species_id">
<glossterm>
Species Id
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>Species id must be specified when loading layouts.  
  Species are associated with ids in the species table when &product; is
  installed.  To determine the species id for a specific species, login
  to the <link linkend="postgres_database">database</link> as the <link
  linkend="postgres_user">postgres user</link> and examine the species
  table.
  </para>
  <example>
  <title>Determining a Species Id
  </title>
  <programlisting>
  $ <command>psql geoss -d geoss</command>
  Password:
  Welcome to psql 7.3.4-RH, the PostgreSQL interactive terminal.

  Type:  \copyright for distribution terms
         \h for help with SQL commands
         \? for help on internal slash commands
         \g or terminate with semicolon to execute query
         \q to quit

geoss=#  <command>select spc_pk, primary_scientific_name, common_names from species;</command>
 spc_pk |    primary_scientific_name    |             common_names             
 --------+-------------------------------+--------------------------------------
     89 | Lycopodium clavatum           | stag's-horn clubmoss
     90 | Chondrus crispus              | carrageen, Irish moss
      5 | Saccharomyces cerevisiae      | yeast

geoss=<command>\q</command>
  </programlisting>
  </example>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>R</title>

<glossentry id="replicate"><glossterm>
  Replicates</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  Replicates can be either different biological subjects or
  technical replicated hybridizations (or chips); these will 
  result in different statistical analysis options and results.
  Consult to the GMB staff for more detailed description.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>U</title>


<glossentry id="university_of_virginia"><glossterm>
  University of Virginia</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  The <ulink url="http://www.virginia.edu">University of
  Virginia</ulink> is where &product; is created and maintained.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="uploaded_files"><glossterm>
  Uploaded Files</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  <link linkend="users">Users</link> can upload several types of files.
  They can upload mas5 data files which they can then use with <link
  linkend="analysis_tree">analysis trees</link>.  They can upload <link
  linkend="criteria_file">criteria files</link>, which they can use to
  build <link linkend="analysis_condition">analysis conditions</link>
  and <link linkend="analysis_set">analysis sets</link>.  They can also
  upload files under the the generic "other" category.  These files
  could then be made viewable to other users.  Examples of such files
  might be write-ups on experiment data.
  </para>
  <para>
  Note that <link linkend="administrator_user">administrators</link> and
  <link linkend="special_center_administrator_user">special center
  administrators</link> can also upload logo and icon files associated
  with <link linkend="special_center">special centers</link>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="users"><glossterm>
  Users</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>Currently, GEOSS supports the following user types:.
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  <link linkend="public_user">Public User</link>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <link linkend="member_user">Member User</link>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <link linkend="array_center_staff_user">Array Center Staff User</link>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <link linkend="administrator_user">Administrator</link>
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist> 
  Additionally, it is possible for a user to be designated as <link
  linkend="special_center_administrator_user">special center administrator
  user.</link> 
  Note, however, that this is not a user type, but rather a
  designation, and such a user will also have one of the four user types
  mentioned above.  
</para>
<note>
Please note that the user type names have recently changed and you may 
encounter instances where the legacy user type is still in use.
Specifically, "member users" used to be "experiment set providers",
"Array Center Staff Users" used to be "curators", and "special center
administrators" used to be "organization curators".  The "public" user
type has not changed.
</note>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="user_file"><glossterm>
  User File</glossterm>
<glossdef>
  <para>
  Individual &product; users own several kinds of files: <link
  linkend="chip_data_files">chip data files</link>, <link
  linkend="analysis_files">analysis files</link> and  <link
  linkend="uploaded_files">uploaded files</link>.  These are the user
  data files.
  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

</glossdiv>

</glossary>
