<book id="overview">
<title>&product; Overview</title>
<article id="introduction_to_&product;">
<title>Introduction to &product;</title>

<para>
The <link linkend="&product;">&product;</link>
project is a rewrite of the original 
GeneX 1.4 project which was initially conceived at 
<ulink
url="http://www.ncgr.org">National Center for Genome Resources (NCGR)
</ulink>
as a proprietary software 
project. Along with two other projects, &product; has emerged from this 
earliest 
version as a direct result of diverging requirements and a need for a 
practical and functional system. &product; is open source and freely available 
at the <ulink url="http://geoss.sourceforge.net/">SourceForge</ulink> web site.
</para>

<para> 
The evolution of &product; continues to be driven by the need to get the 
greatest use of gene expression data. Developers at the <ulink
url="http://www.virginia.edu">University of Virginia</ulink>, 
through modification and innovation, have created a secure, 
web based relational database management system that allows users to load, 
archive, manage and analyze gene expression data. 
</para>

<para>&product; includes: 
<orderedlist numberation="arabic">
<listitem>
 <para>
 A convenient user interface based on the workflow of biomedical microarray 
 research. Investigators login via a web browser to enter a variety of 
 general and 
 <link linkend="miame">MIAME</link> required information pertaining to their 
 <link linkend="array_study">array studies</link>, 
 <link linkend="experiment_condition">experimental conditions</link>, 
 <link linkend="sample">samples</link>, and
 <link linkend="hybridization">hybridizations</link>. 
 </para>
 <para>
 The <link linkend="array_center">array center</link>
 has been supplied with a number of online processing 
 tools which allow them to track and bill <link
 linkend="array_order">array orders</link>, create reports, and 
 manage work load. 
 <link linkend="special_center">Special center</link>
 support is included so the array center 
 can adjust their array order approval and billing practices 
 according to each 
 center's individual requirements. 
 </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
A web tool that allows each user to post his array data for public 
access. Public data can be viewed and downloaded from the main &product; web 
site without a user account. It can also be analyzed via the &product; set 
of analysis tools by simply creating a public access account. In addition, 
personal data can be analyzed once uploaded to the &product; system. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
An innovative 
<link linkend="analysis_tree">Analysis Tree</link> 
interface that can interactively incorporate 
different analytical tools into a unified analysis tree.
 &product; is a database 
combined with an integrated toolset to enable researchers to analyze their 
data, and in some circumstances to make a comparative reference to public 
data. Text delimited data sets can be uploaded, regardless of technology, 
to be analyzed.
</para>
<para>
The current <link linkend="analysis">analysis</link> tools include:

  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
     up-to-date statistical methods for 
     discovering differential expression patterns in microarray data: t-test, 
     SAM, permutation test, and LPE (Local Pooled Error) test, especially the 
     last recommended for small-sample (less than six replicated arrays per 
     condition) microarray data analysis,
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
   statistical and functional filtering, 
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    annotation tool which can provide many different types of annotation 
    and functional information, and 
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    hierarchical clustering tool which 
    provides both cluster-image-map and direct links to 
    <ulink url="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov">National Center for Biotechnology
    Information (NCBI)</ulink> 
    genome information sites for each microarray data set analyzed.
   </listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>
</article>

<article id="history_of_&product;">
<title>History of &product;</title>
  <para>
  The &product; project is a rewrite of the original GeneX project
  which was initially conceived at 
  <ulink
  url="http://www.ncgr.org">National Center for Genome Resources (NCGR)
  </ulink>
  .  The original GeneX is 
  largely considered to be a prototype and has been leveraged in the
  development of three separate projects:

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
  
  <listitem>
  <para>
  <ulink url="http://geoss.sourceforge.net/">&product;</ulink> 
  </para>
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  <para>
  <ulink url="http://genex.sourceforge.net/">GeneX 2</ulink> 
  </para>
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  <para>
  <ulink url="http://www.ncgr.org/genex/">GeneX-Lite</ulink> 
  </para>
  </listitem>

 </itemizedlist>
  
  All three projects have emerged from this
  early version as a direct result of diverging requirements
  and a need for a practical and functional system.
  &product; is composed of a relational database, 
  a web-based user interface and an analysis system. 
  </para>
  <para>
  Although &product; is historically related to the original GeneX project,
  it has diverged considerably and has an entirely new code base. The original 
  name of &product; was GeneX-Va since it was created at the University 
  of Virginia with the involvement of the <ulink
  url="http://vabioinfo.org/">Virginia Bioinformatics
  Consortium (VBC)</ulink>.
  </para>
      
  <para>
   A small team at the University of Virginia rewrote Genex 1.4 and 
   released Genex Va 1.5 in October of 2002.   Since that time many
   upgrades have been made and there are frequent new releases.
   In 2004 GeneX-Va was renamed to &product;
   to more accurately reflect its 
   framework and to avoid any confusion among project names.  The product is installed and
   used regularly by the UVa <link linkend="array_center">array center</link>
   and  UVa researchers.  Development on the project is on-going as we
   continue to add new functionality and improve on the user interface.
  </para> 
</article>

<article id="&product;_developers">
<title>&product; Developers</title>

<formalpara>
<title>Dr. Jae K Lee</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Associate Professor
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<ulink url="http://www.virginia.edu/">University of Virginia</ulink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<ulink url="http://www.healthsystem.virginia.edu/internet/hes/">Health
Evaluation Sciences</ulink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<email>jaeklee@virginia.edu</email>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<ulink
url="http://healthsystem.virginia.edu/internet/hes/biostat/docs/personnel/lee.cfm">Dr.
Lee</ulink> holds a PhD in statistical genetics from the University of
Wisconsin-Madison and has a wealth of bioinformatics experience.  He 
manages the &product; project and provides product direction in 
requirements, collaborations, publication, and resources.  
</formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Teela James</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
  <para>
Technical Team Leader
  </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>
<ulink url="http://www.virginia.edu/">University of Virginia</ulink>
  </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>
<ulink url="http://www.healthsystem.virginia.edu/internet/hes/">Health
Evaluation Sciences</ulink>
  </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>
<email>teela-virginia@peff.net</email>
  </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
Teela James is responsible for
the implementation and integration of all new software components and
for maintaining the existing code base.  Her additions to the project
have included public user functionality, the addition of special
centers, public data publication, the addition of the administrator
user and graphical administrator tools, and creation of the analysis
trees infrastructure. 
</formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>
Jodi Kanter
</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
  <para>
Bioinformatics Database Administrator
  </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>
<ulink url="http://www.virginia.edu/">University of Virginia</ulink>
  </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>
<ulink url="http://www.itc.virginia.edu/achs/">
Academic Computing Health Sciences</ulink>
  </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>
<email>jkanter@virginia.edu</email>
  </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
Jodi Kanter designed, implemented, and maintains the &product; database.
Additionally, Jodi manages product testing and support.
</formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>
Dawn Adelsberger
</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
  <para>
System Administrator
  </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>
<ulink url="http://www.virginia.edu/">University of Virginia</ulink>
  </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>
<ulink url="http://www.itc.virginia.edu/achs/">
Academic Computing Health Sciences</ulink>
  </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>
<email>dma9w@virginia.edu</email>
  </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
Dawn Adelsberger performs system administrator for UVa's &product;
installation.
</formalpara>


<formalpara>
<title>
Dr. HyungJun Cho
</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
  <para>
Bioinformatics Analysis Developer
  </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>
<ulink url="http://www.virginia.edu/">University of Virginia</ulink>
  </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>
<ulink url="http://www.healthsystem.virginia.edu/internet/hes/">Health
Evaluation Sciences</ulink>
  </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>
<email>hcho@virginia.edu</email>
  </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
HyungJun Cho is a Bioinformatics specialist and biostatistician.  He is
responsible for writing and refining analysis routines. 
</formalpara>


<formalpara>
<title>
Tom Laudeman
</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
  <para>
Software Developer
  </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>
<ulink url="http://www.virginia.edu/">University of Virginia</ulink>
  </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>
<ulink url="http://www.itc.virginia.edu/achs/">
Academic Computing Health Sciences</ulink>
  </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>
<email>twl8n@virginia.edu</email>
  </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
Tom Laudeman is the former technical lead on the &product; project.
Although he is not actively working on &product; at this time, he is
responsible for the initial design and implementation of &product;
including web site generation, installation, and system integration.
</formalpara>

<para>
Additional contributions have been made by the following individuals:
</para>

<formalpara>
<title>
Jennifer Weller
</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
  <para>
<ulink url="http://www.gmu.edu/">George Mason University</ulink>
  </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
Jennifer Weller was one of the founding members of the original GeneX
project.  Her specialties include computational biology, gene expression
analysis, and gene ontology.
</formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>
Karen Schlauch
</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
  <para>
<ulink url="http://www.gmu.edu/">George Mason University</ulink>
  </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
Karen Schlauch is a mathematician and programmer.  The 
&product; clustering analysis is mostly her work.
</formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>
Jason Stewart
</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
  <para>
<ulink url="http://openinformatics.sourceforge.net/">OpenInformatics.org</ulink>
  </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
Jason Stewart is a founding member of the original GeneX project and has
been instrumental in the continued progress of GeneX as open source
software.  He wrote all the core object classes used in GeneX versions
prior to 1.5.x and continues to build GeneX 2.  While primarily a
software developer, he has vast knowledge on gene expression and issues
related to capturing gene expression data.
</formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>
Greg Riddick</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
  <para>
<ulink url="http://www.virginia.edu/">University of Virginia</ulink>
  </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>
<email>gr3k@virginia.edu</email>
  </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
Greg Riddick is a biochemist, programmer, and bioinformatics specialist.
He ported the clustering analysis routine, and built the functionality
to draw a tree from the clustering output.
</formalpara>

</article>

<article id="home_page">
<title>Home Page</title>
<para>
The home page provides an introduction to the product and
provides a starting point for all &product; activity. <link
linkend="users">Users</link> can login via the login interface on the
left side bar.  If they are already logged in, there is an "Already
logged in" link to take them directory to the appropriate set of GUI
tools for their user type.  Non-users may make use of several
publicly available functions including <link
linkend="view_public_data">downloading and viewing public gene
data</link>, <link linkend="request_an_account">requesting a &product;
account</link> on that installation, reviewing <link
linkend="&product;_documentation">&product; documentation</link>, 
or <link linkend="&product;_downloads">downloading &product; source</link>.
</para>
<para>
Depending on the installation, there may be several other items
viewable.  Logos of supported <link linkend="special_center">special
centers</link> may be displayed on the left hand side of the page.
Additionally, there may be special descriptive or news items of interest
to users of that installation on the page.  An example of a news item
would be a &product; training session being provided.  
These items are configured by the <link
linkend="administrator_user">Administrator</link> for each installation
via the <link linkend="configure_&product;">Configure &product;</link>
link.
</para>

<sect1 id="view_public_data">
<title>View Public Data</title>
<para>
If a researcher chooses to publish their experiment data on &product;,
it will be available via the "View Public Data" link.  Each box on this
page represents one study.  Currently, there are no special
navigational/search controls for this page, but that is planned for
future development.</para>
<para>
Each study is delimited in a separate box.  The first items displayed
are the study name, a short description, and the name of the <link
linkend="primary_investigator">PI</link>.  The first link provides <link
linkend="miame">MIAME</link> information about the study in either text
or html format.  Following that are the <link
linkend="chip_data_files">chip data files</link> associated with the
study.  Files can be downloaded by clicking on the link.
</para>

<para>
Occasionally, if a study has just be published, data may be unavailable.
If this is the case, a message to that effect will be returned.  This
likely means that the <link linkend="public_data_administrator">public
data administrator</link> is verifying the publication information, and
the files will be posted shortly.  If the files are not available after
several days, contact the <link linkend="administrator_user">&product;
administrator</link> for that installation.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="request_an_account">
<title>Request An Account</title>
<para>
This link allows non-users to request an account on a specific &product;
installation.  For security reasons, not all installations support all
<link linkend="users">account types</link>.  If not all account
types are supported there may be a link to a <link
linkend="companion_installation">companion installation</link> that
supports the missing types.</para>
<para>
To request an account, first select the desired account type, then
click 'Next'.  Then fill out the fields for account generation.
&mandatory;  Although an email address is not required for some user
types, it is highly recommended that you provide one as &product; sends
emails to communicate details regarding account creation and <link
linkend="analysis">analysis</link> results.</para>
<para>
An email containing account details is send immediately if the request
is for a <link linkend="public_user">public user</link> account.  If the
request is for a different account type, the response email may take a
couple days, as it is necessary for the <link
linkend="administrator_user">administrator</link> to verify validity of
the account request.
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="&product;_documentation">
<title>&product; Documentation</title>
<para>
The &product; Documentation links provide access to all product
documentation.  The documentation is divided into sections based on
<link linkend="users">user type</link>.  Each section contains overview
articles that provide general discussion of specific tasks that type of
user may wish to perform, a detailed discussion of each of the GUI
options available to that type of user, and an FAQ section.  If you have
questions that are not addressed by the documentation or have noticed
inaccuracies in the documentation, please email <link
linkend="&product;_developers">
&product; developers</link>
 so that the concern can be answered and documentation modified
 accordingly.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="&product;_downloads">
<title>&product; Downloads</title>
Currently, &product; downloads are available from the SourceForge.  The
downloads link from &product; home page takes the user directly to the
relevant page.
</sect1>

</article>
</book>
