<part id="special_center_workflow">
<title>Overview: Workflows for Special Center Administrator Users</title>
<para>
<link linkend="special_center">Special centers</link> group <link
linkend="users">users</link> who have similar processing needs that
differ slightly from regular users.  In particular, these users may have
access to billing discounts by virtue of their association to the
special center.  In some cases, their <link
linkend="array_order">array orders</link> may require approval by
special center staff before the discounts are applied.
</para>
<para>
For example, the <ulink url="http://genes.med.virginia.edu">UVa
&product; install</ulink> has two special centers configured: the
Digestive Center and the Cancer Center.  These centers correspond to
groups at <ulink url="http://www.virginia.edu/">UVa</ulink> that have
negotiated discounts on array center processing fees for their members
with the <link linkend="array_center">array center</link>.
</para>
<para>
The <link linkend="special_center_administrator_user">special center
administrator(s)</link> are responsible for managing <link
linkend="special_center">special centers</link>.  The tasks involve
maintaining the list of special center members, keeping center contact
information current, and potentially approving orders.  Information on
each of these tasks is provided below.</para>
<article id="center_management">
<title>Center Management</title>
<para>
<link linkend="special_center">Special center</link> management involves
keeping information regarding the center and center membership current.
Although the <link linkend="administrator_user">&product;
administrator</link> can modify all this information, the special center
administrator is in a much better position to be aware of changes in the
special center and is thus responsible for maintaining the information.</para>
<sect1 id="manage_center_information">
<title>Manage Center Information</title>
<para>
It is important to keep contact information current.  Special center
administrators can update information about the organization including
description, phone number, url, logo, icon, and array order approval
requirements.  All edits are performed via the <link
linkend="edit_special_center_information">Edit special center
information</link> link accessible from <link
linkend="special_center_gui">&center_home;</link>.  Note, however, that
if you wish to change the logo or icon associated with a special center,
you will have to upload the logo file via the <link
linkend="upload_logo_or_icon_file">Upload logo/icon file</link> link
prior to  modifying the logo or icon file from "Edit special center
information".
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="manage_center_members">
<title>Manage Center Members</title>
<para>
It is also the responsibility of the special center administrator to
ensure appropriate membership in the special center.  Normally, when
<link linkend="users">users</link> <link
linkend="request_an_account">request an account</link> they will
indicate with special centers they belong to.  The &product; <link
linkend="administrator_user">Administrator</link> will verify the new
user's association with the special center prior to creating the account
and will ensure that user is a member of the special center when
creating the account.  However, if users become disassociated with the
special center, the special center administrator needs to modify the
membership list to reflect that change.  Additionally, if a current
&product; user becomes a member of the special center, the special
center administrator should make that change as well.  
</para>
<para>
Membership list maintenance is accomplished via the <link
linkend="edit_special_center_members">Edit special center members</link>
accessible via <link linkend="special_center_gui">&center_home;</link>.
</para>
</sect1>
</article>
<article id="approving_orders">
<title>Approving Orders</title>
<para>
Array centers may be configured so that <link
linkend="array_order">array orders</link> require approval.  Generally,
when a user finishes configuring their array order, they submit it.  The
<link linkend="array_center_staff_user">array center staff</link>
receive an email stating that the array order configuration is complete
and the order is ready for processing.  However, if the array order is
associated with a special center that requires orders to be approved,
the procedure includes an extra step.  In that instance, when an order
is submitted, instead of emailing array center staff, the special center
administrator is emailed and notified that the array order is ready for
processing.  Next, the array order must be approved by the special
center administrator.  Only once it is approved by the special center
administrator is the notification sent to the array center staff.
</para>
<para>
Array center staff can approve orders via two interfaces: the <link
linkend="approve_orders">Approve Orders</link> link and the <link
linkend="special_center_view_reports">View Reports</link> link, both
accessible via <link linkend="special_center_gui">&center_home;</link>.
</para>
</article>
</part>
