<part id="special_center_gui">
<title>Center Home: The Special Center Administrator GUI Tool</title>
<para>
<link linkend="special_center_administrator_user">Special center
administrators</link> can perform all necessary administration functions
from &center_home;.  Note that if you are a special center administrator
for more than one special center, each link will first require you to
identify which special center you are currently administering prior to
granting you access to the specified function.
</para>
<article id="special_center_management">
<sect1 id="approve_orders">
<title>Approve Orders</title>
<para>
This link allows administrators to review and approve <link
linkend="array_order">array orders</link>.  To approve an order, enter
any relevant comments in the "Approval Comments" field and click on the
"Approve Order" button associated with the specific order.  Note that
there are several other links on the page that allow the special center
administrator to view further information on the owner and creator of
the array order and on the associated study.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="special_center_view_reports">
<title>View Reports</title>
<para>
<link linkend="special_center_administrator_user">Special center
administrators</link> can use this link to view information on <link
linkend="array_order">array orders</link> associated with the <link
linkend="special_center">special center</link>.  The following fields
are included in the report:
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      <link linkend="order_number">Order Number</link>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        An order number is assigned to each array order requested by a
        <link linkend="users">user</link>.  This unique identifier links
        the samples to a particular study and set of experimental
        conditions.  In the report, the order number is presented as a
        link.  Clicking on the link is one way to access the page to
        approve a specific array order.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Is Approved
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        This column provides the date in which the array order
        was approved or notes if it has not been approved yet.          
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Approval Comments
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The special center administrator can choose to list comments
        when approving orders.  These comments are displayed here.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      <link linkend="order_status">Order Status</link>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        This field lists the status of the array order.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Study
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        This field lists the <link linkend="array_study">array
        study</link> associated with the array order.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Study Comments
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        This field lists the comments associated with the array study.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      <link linkend="primary_investigator">PI</link> Name
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        This field lists the name of the PI who owns the data.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist> 
Note that the report can be sorted on any of the columns by pressing the
button that is the column header.
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="edit_special_center_members">
<title>Edit Special Center Members</title>
<para>
This link allows the <link
linkend="special_center_administrator_user">special center
administrator</link> to add and remove members from their <link
linkend="special_center">special center.</link>  When adding <link
linkend="users">users</link> to the special center, their role must be
specified (i.e. regular member or administrator member).</para>
<para>
To remove a user from the special center, check the checkbox under
"Remove User" that is in the same row as the <link
linkend="&product;_login_id">login id</link> for the user you wish to
remove.  Then click "Modify Members".  Several users may be removed
simultaneously.</para>
<para>
To add a user to the special center as a regular member, check the
checkbox under "Add User" that is in the same row as the login id for
the user you wish to add.  Then click "Modify Members".  To add a user
to the special center as another special center administrator, check the
checkbox under "Add Curator" that is in the same row as the login id for
the user you wish to add.  Then click "Modify Members".  Several users
may be added simultaneously.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="edit_special_center_information">
<title>Edit Special Center Information</title>
<para>
The <link linkend="special_center_administrator_user">special center
administrator</link> can use this link to modify the specifics of their
<link linkend="special_center">special center</link>.  Special centers
have the following characteristics:

<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Special Center Name
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        This field is set by the <link
        linkend="administrator_user">&product; administrator</link> 
        when the special center is created.  It can not be modified by
        the special center administrator, but is displayed for
        informational purposes.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Special Center Description
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        This field provides a brief description of the organization.
        Currently, it is only displayed to the &product; administrator
        for informational purposes.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Special Center Phone Number
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        This is the contact number that the &product; administrator
        should use to contact the special center should
        the need arise.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Billing Discount
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The <link linkend="array_center_staff_user">array center
        staff</link> inform the &product; administrator about the
        discount agreement for a special center.  Only the &product;
        administrator can modify this value, but it is displayed here
        for informational purposes.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Special Center URL
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        This field displays the URL to to the
        special center web site. It is used when the special center has
        a logo displayed on the <link linkend="home_page">&product; home 
        page</link>. The logo is linked to this URL.                     
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Special Center Logo
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        This field allows the special center administrator to assign a
        logo to the special center.  Simply choose the appropriate logo
        file from drop down box.  Only files that have been uploaded
        via the <link linkend="upload_logo_or_icon_file">Upload
        Logo/Icon File</link> link are available as options.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Special Center Icon
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        This field allows the special center administrator to assign a
        icon to the special center.  Simply choose the appropriate icon
        file from drop down box.  Only files that have been uploaded
        via the <link linkend="upload_logo_or_icon_file">Upload
        Logo/Icon File</link> link are available as options.
      </para>
      <note>
        Although you can set an icon file, it is not yet used by the
        system.  That functionality will be implemented in a future
        release.
      </note>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Orders Require Approval Before Array Center Processing
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Special center administrators can set whether they want to
        manually approve <link linkend="array_order">array orders</link>
        or whether approval should be automatic.  Check the box for
        manual approval.  
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="upload_logo_or_icon_file">
<title>Upload logo/icon file</title>
<para>
Depending on how the <link linkend="administrator_user">administrator
</link> has configured the <link linkend="special_center">special center
</link>, the special center may be allowed to place their logo on the
home page of the &product; installation.  In order to designate a logo,
you must first upload it.  This link can be used to upload logo files.
Once the logo has been uploaded, you will need to associate it with the
special center.  This is done via that <link
linkend="edit_special_center_information">Edit Special Center
Information</link> link.  
</para>
<para>
Icons can also be uploaded, but they are not yet used by the system.
Eventually, the icons will be to associated users with special centers,
but this feature is not yet implemented.
</para>
<para>
To upload a file, specify where the file is a logo or an icon.  Then use
the "Choose File" button to identify the file to upload.  It is not
necessary to specify a filename if you want the filename to remain the
same.  However, if you would like to rename the file, you may specify
the new filename in the "Filename" field.  Click "Upload" to upload the
file.
</para>
</sect1>
</article>
</part>
