<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="analysis_tutorial">
<title>Analysis Tutorial</title>
<para>
This document is prepared to help GEOSS users to run analysis trees and interpret the results. 
For our illustration here, analysis trees are gradually constructed and illustrated by adding analysis nodes 
and explaining their results one at a time, 
while the final analysis tree contains most of the current analysis routines on the system. 
However, different combinations of analysis tools and their corresponding options can be used in an analysis tree.
</para>

<sect1 id="analysis_tutorial_quality_control">
<title>Quality Control</title>
<para>
Once an analysis tree is created, the first analysis routine is usually recommended with 'Quality Control'.
 This provides statistical and graphical assessment of array data quality and the IQR (inter-quartile-range) 
 and lowess (local regression) normalization procedures.
</para>

<imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="../graphics/quality_control.gif" format="GIF"></imagedata>
</imageobject>

<para>
When you run the simple tree by clicking 'Run Analysis', you see a message for your run. C
licking 'file repository' takes you to the file repository like 'View my files'. T
he file you may want to look at is the 'Quality_Control_-_Scatter_Plot.pdf'. 
This is a scatter plot matrix graph of all the chips in the data file you previously chose.
These scatter plot show the correlation and distribution patterns among the replicates 
in the same condition and among the chips between different conditions. 
The assumption is that the replicate chips should look much more similar to 
each other than the chips from different conditions and 
that the relationship is generally linear across all intensity ranges. 
For example, if two chips are very similar and highly reproducible, 
the data points should concentrate along the 45-degree line in the scatter plot. 
The more the points are scattered away from the 45-degree line, 
the more dissimilar the chips are. Sometimes the scatter plots show a non-linear curvature, 
often near the origin. In that case it is recommended to do "lowess normalization". 
This simple tree can be rerun with the lowess normalization by checking the box for 
'Perform lowess normalization' in the tree. 
If unusual patterns persist, it is recommended to consult with the GMB (GeneChip/Micorarray Bioinformatics) 
core staff (refer to the GEOSS home page for further information).
</para>

<imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="../graphics/quality_control_plot.gif" format="GIF"></imagedata>
</imageobject>

<para>
The second file you may want to look at is 'Quality_Control_-_Correlation_and_Specificity_and_Sensitivity.txt'.
This file includes specificity and sensitivity. Specificity, or reproducibility, 
is the average correlation between replicated arrays within each condition. 
Sensitivity is the difference between specificity and average correlation between non-replicated arrays. 
If sensitivity is large in the positive direction, 
there are often many genes differentially expressed between different conditions, 
vice versa.
</para>

<imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="../graphics/quality_control_text.gif" format="GIF"></imagedata>
</imageobject>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="analysis_tutorial_differential_discovery">
<title>Differential Discovery</title>
<para>
The next node you may want to add to your analysis is 'Differential Discovery', 
which evaluates statistical significance of differential expression, together with fold change values. 
The two-sample t-test, Westfall and Young's permutation test, LPE (Local Pooled Error) test, 
and SAM (Significance Analysis of Microarrays) test are performed in this node.
These statistical tests can be used to discover differentially expressed genes under two conditions. 
If there are more than two conditions, all pairs of the conditions are examined. 
The two-sample t-test is the most popular procedure for comparing means of two conditions and the Westfall and Young's 
permutation test is a resampling-based procedure. Genes with small p-values from the tests are claimed as significant, 
i.e., differentially expressed. The LPE test has high statistical power for array data with a small number of replicates 
(e.g., duplicate or triplicate) because it precisely estimates baseline error variances by pooling genes with similar expression levels. 
The LPE test provides FDRs (False Discovery Rates), as well as z-statistics and p-values. 
FDR is used to control the average proportion of false positives among all positives, 
so select genes with low FDRs. SAM uses a variance stabilizing factor to improve variance estimation in low-replicated array data. 
SAM also provides FDR-based q-values as well as d-statistics. 
Note that LPE z-statistics/p-value and SAM d-statistic are computed as defaults; 
however, LPE FDR and SAM q-value can be computed by selecting boxes in the (Optional) differential discovery. 
The LPE FDR and SAM q-value require a considerable computing time.
</para>

<imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="../graphics/differential_discovery.gif" format="GIF"></imagedata>
</imageobject>

<para>
When you run the tree, the main output file 'Differential_Discovery_-_Differential_Signal_Data.txt' is produced and saved in the file repository 
('View my files' in File Management). It is generally a big file (&gt;2 MB). To view the content more easily, 
download the file onto your machine and then open it in MS Excel.
</para>


<imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="../graphics/differential_discovery_out.gif" format="GIF"></imagedata>
</imageobject>

<para>
There are quite a few columns, depending on the number of chips and conditions in the data file you chose in the analysis. 
For example, here are the column headings:
</para>

<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para>
Probe.Set
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
X04.01_naive_A_3
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
X04.01_naive_A_2
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
X04.01_naive_A_1
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
X04.01_clone_A_3
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
X04.01_clone_A_2
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
X04.01_clone_A_1
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
X04.01_48hour_A_3
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
X04.01_48hour_A_2
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
X04.01_48hour_A_1
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
TRADFOLD-naive-clone
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
TRADFOLD-naive-48hour
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
TRADFOLD-clone-48hour
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
LOGFOLD-naive-clone
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
LOGFOLD-naive-48hour
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
LOGFOLD-clone-48hour
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
T-statistic- naive VS clone
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
T.p.value- naive VS clone
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Bonferroni.p- naive VS clone
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Permutation.p- naive VS clone
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
T-statistic- naive VS 48hour
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
T.p.value- naive VS 48hour
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Bonferroni.p- naive VS 48hour
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Permutation.p- naive VS 48hour
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
T-statistic- clone VS 48hour
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
T.p.value- clone VS 48hour
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Bonferroni.p- clone VS 48hour
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Permutation.p- clone VS 48hour
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
LPE.z.statistic- naive VS clone
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
LPE.p.value- naive VS clone
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
LPE.z.statistic- naive VS 48hour
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
LPE.p.value- naive VS 48hour
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
LPE.z.statistic- clone VS 48hour
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
LPE.p.value- clone VS 48hour
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
SAM.d.statistic- naive VS clone
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
SAM.d.statistic- naive VS 48hour
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
SAM.d.statistic- clone VS 48hour
</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>
Columns 2 to 10 contain normalized expression data. For each pair of conditions,  
the results of t-test and permutation test (columns 17 to 28), LPE test (columns 29 to 34), 
SAM test (columns 35 to 37) are provided. Additional columns for LPE FDR and 
SAM q-value can be added if they are computed by checking their boxes. 
Fold-changes are presented in columns 11 to 16. A traditional fold change takes
 the average of gene expressions for each condition, divides the two averages, 
 and then takes the log of the ratio. A log fold change transforms the expressions to log scale, 
 takes the average, and then takes the difference between the two averages. These two different ways 
 of fold-change calculation generally provide very similar results, but sometimes may differ due to extreme values a
 nd ratios; in those cases, the latter fold-change value may be preferred, 
 but more careful attention is required for such outliers.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="analysis_tutorial_filter">
<title>Filter</title>

<para>
This routine gives some options to subset the genes based on the statistical analysis results above 
and/or functional key words. 
To filter genes, this routine also provides annotations, such as gene symbol, gene name, unigene ID, locus ID, chromosome location, and gene ontology.
Since there are often several pair-wise comparisons between the conditions, 
you may need to select a specific pair of conditions for your selection. 
The filter routine can subset the gene probes based on one or two statistical criteria, 
such as p-value from the LPE test and a fold value from Log Fold Change. 
Note that if LPE FDR or SAM q-value is used for filtering, it must be run in 'Differential Discover'.
</para>


<imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="../graphics/filter1.gif" format="GIF"></imagedata>
</imageobject>

<imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="../graphics/filter2.gif" format="GIF"></imagedata>
</imageobject>


<para>
A subset of genes can be obtained by entering  one or more key words in 'Functional Filtering', 
where key words must be separated by a coma (,).  
Also, a file containing a list of genes (probe set IDs or gene symbols) can be uploaded for filtering. 
The filter file should contain a list of genes in the one column (one per one row). 
Genes with the probe set IDs (or gene symbols) in the filter file are selected and 
marked by '+' in the last column of the output file. 
If the box for 'Include all genes in the filter file' is checked, all the genes in the filter file uploaded are included 
regralress of their significance.	
If the box for 'Include all significant genes' is checked, all the significant genes are included 
in addition to genes in the filter file. 
If both boxes are unchecked, only the genes that are significant and 
in the filter file are included.
If both boxes are checked, the genes that are significant or in the filter file are included. 	
</para>

<para>
You need to limit the number of gene probes for further investigation because if 1900 or more genes are kept, 
the files generated with 'Cluster' will not be viewable with Acrobat Reader. 
The conditions of expression values  can be re-ordered by entering order numbers (e.g., 3, 1, 1) in 'Condition order'. 
If you do not want to re-order, leave the boxes  blanks.
</para>

<imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="../graphics/filter_out.gif" format="GIF"></imagedata>
</imageobject>

<para>
The results are saved in two text files "Filter_-_Filtered_Signal_Data_and_Comparison_Data.txt" and "Filter_-_Filtered_Signal_Data.txt", 
which contain the expression values of all the genes (across all conditions) that meet the selection criteria specified in the filter routine. 
The file "Filter_-_Filtered_Signal_Data.txt" is used as an input for a cluster analysis and the file "Filter_-_Filtered_Signal_Data_and_Comparison_Data.txt" 
contains statistical results in addition to expression values.  For example, the file may be open as an Excel spreadsheet as shown below.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="analysis_tutorial_cluster">
<title>Cluster</title>
<para>
Next, you may want to run a clustering analysis on the subset. This is done by adding node 'Cluster', 
which performs the hierarchical clustering analysis.  Log with base 2 transformation is usually taken 
for clustering as well as differential discovery, so it should be set to True unless log2 transformation is taken elsewhere.  U
sers can choose a measure of similarity (or dissimilarity) between genes (or clusters of genes) 
and one of the following clustering procedures: average linkage (average distance), 
complete linkage (maximum distance or farthest neighbor), and single linkage (minimum distance or nearest neighbor).
</para>

<imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="../graphics/cluster.gif" format="GIF"></imagedata>
</imageobject>

<para>
The result of 'Cluster' is a picture showing the clustering of the selected gene probes. 
It is saved in file 'Cluster_-_Hierarchical_Clustering_Tree.pdf'. Running the tree with the five nodes produces several output files. 
You can see the list by clicking 'View my files' in File Management.
</para>


<imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="../graphics/cluster_out.gif" format="GIF"></imagedata>
</imageobject>

<para>
From this run, 'tdout.pdf' contains the hierarchical clustering tree with direct links to the NCBI's 
web site based on their gene accession numbers. This graphic is zoomable (using a standard pdf viewer, such as Adobe Acrobat) 
and in high quality for manuscript and grant preparations.
</para>


<imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="../graphics/ncbi.gif" format="GIF"></imagedata>
</imageobject>

<para>
In the tree dendogram, genes with similar expression patterns are linked in lower levels. 
This can be confirmed in a heat map. High expression intensities are represented by red, 
while low expression intensities are represented by green. Black indicates medium intensities.
For a direct link to the NCBI's web site in this plot, 
click a gene accession number, resulting in a link to the following website.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="analysis_tutorial_summary1">
<title>Summary I</title>

<para>
For your first round of analyis, you may want to focus on the following five files from the last analysis tree shown above:
</para>

<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para> File 'Quality_Control_-_Scatter_Plot.pdf' showing the
scatter plot matrix from the <link
linkend="analysis_tutorial_quality_control">Quality Control</link> node.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
File 'Quality_Control_-_Correlation_and_Specificity_and_Sensitivity.txt'
containing the correlation matrix, plus sensitivity and specificity,
from the <link linkend="analysis_tutorial_quality_control">Qulity
Control</link>  node.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
File 'Differential_Discovery_-_Differential_Signal_Data.txt' containing
results of statistical analysis for discovery of differentially
expressed genes from the <link
linkend="analysis_tutorial_differential_discovery">Differntial
Discovery</link> node.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
File 'Filter_-_Filtered_Signal_Data_and_Comparison_Data.txt' containing
a subset of 'Differential_Discovery_-_Differential_Signal_Data.txt' by
your choice in the <link linkend="analysis_tutorial_filter">Filter</link> node.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
File 'Cluster_-_Hierarchical_Clustering_Tree.pdf' that containing a
cluster plot of genes, from the <link linkend="analysis_tutorial_cluster">Cluster</link>
node.
</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>
The rest of the files on the list are some log files that keep track of
how a node has been run and what options have been selected for a
particular node. Such log files may help you to reconstruct (reproduce)
your analysis later.  However, it may require familiarity with the use
of GEOSS analysis interface for their full utilization.  There are some
intermediate data files that transfer the results of one node to the
next.  The interpretation of the results from a more complex analysis
can be supported by the GMB core staff (refer to the GEOSS home page for
the procedure).
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="analysis_tutorial_multicondition">
<title>Multi-Condition Differential Discovery and Filter</title>
<para>
When you have more than two conditions, you may want to compare all the
conditions simultaneously rather than pairs of the conditions.  The
'Multi-Condition Differential Discovery' module evaluates statistical
significance of differential expression under all the conditions.  ANOVA
(Analysis of Variance) and HEM (Heterogeneous Error Model) analyses are
performed in this node.  ANOVA is the most popular procedure for
comparing means of multiple conditions and WY(Westfall &amp; Young) and
BH (Benjamini &amp; Hochberg) tests are resampling-based procedurse.
Genes with small p-values from the tests are claimed as significant,
i.e., differentially expressed.  HEM is a Bayesian or emprical Bayes
procedure for comparing multiple conditions, which is statistically
powerful, particularly, with a small number of replicates.  HEM provides
FDRs (False Discovery Rates), as well as H-statistics.  FDR is used to
control the average proportion of false positives among all positives,
so select genes with low FDRs. 
</para>


<para>
Like the 'Filter' module, the 'Multi-Condition Filter' module gives some
options to subset the genes based on the statistical analysis results
above  and/or functional key words.  The results are saved in two text
files
"Multi-Condition_Filter_-_Filtered_Signal_Data_and_Comparison_Data.txt"
and "Multi-Condition_Filter_-_Filtered_Signal_Data.txt", which contain
the expression values of all the genes (across all conditions) that meet
the selection criteria specified in the filter routine.  The file
"Multi-Condition_Filter_-_Filtered_Signal_Data.txt" is used as an input
for a cluster analysis and the file
"Multi-Condition_Filter_-_Filtered_Signal_Data_and_Comparison_Data.txt"
contains statistical results in addition to expression values.  Note
that 'Quality Control'and 'Cluster' are the same as above.
</para>

<imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="../graphics/multicond.gif" format="GIF"></imagedata>
</imageobject>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="analysis_tutorial_summary2">
<title>Summary II</title>

<para>
For your multi-condition analyis, you may want to focus on the following
five files from the last analysis tree shown above:
</para>

<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para>
File 'Quality_Control_-_Scatter_Plot.pdf' showing the scatter plot
matrix from the  <link
linkend="analysis_tutorial_quality_control">Qulity Control</link> node.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
File 'Quality_Control_-_Correlation_and_Specificity_and_Sensitivity.txt'
containing the correlation matrix, plus sensitivity and specificity,
from the <link linkend="analysis_tutorial_quality_control">Quality
Control</link>  node.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
File
'Multi-Condition_Differential_Discovery_-_Differential_Signal_Data.txt'
containing results of statistical analysis for discovery of
differentially expressed genes from the <link
linkend="analysis_tutorial_differential_discovery">Differential
Discovery</link> node.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
File
'Multi-Condition_Filter_-_Filtered_Signal_Data_and_Comparison_Data.txt'
containing a subset of
'Differential_Discovery_-_Differential_Signal_Data.txt' by your choice
in the <link linkend="analysis_tutorial_filter">Filter</link> node.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
File 'Cluster_-_Hierarchical_Clustering_Tree.pdf' that containing a
cluster plot of genes, from the <link
linkend="analysis_tutorial_cluster">Cluster</link>
node.
</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>


</sect1>

</article>
