<part id="user_faq">
<title>FAQ</title>
<qandaset>

<qandadiv id="user_faq_analysis"><title>Analysis</title></qandadiv>
<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
      My analysis didn't generate result files.  What happened?
    </para>
  </question>
  <answer>
    <para>
      If you have waited the appropriate amount of time and there are no
      output files, then one of the analysis modules has crashed.  See
      <link linkend="troubleshooting_tree_failures">Troubleshooting Tree
      Failures</link> for information on determining why the tree
      crashed.  
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
      Why can't I view the results of the treedraw analysis? 
    </para>
  </question>
  <answer>
    <para>
      If you are trying to view the results of the treedraw analysis
      using Acrobat Reader and Reader crashes, you may have run treedraw
      with too many input rows.  You may either view the output pdf
      using a different pdf viewer, like xpdf, or you should restrict
      the number of rows that treedraw takes as input.   
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandadiv id="user_faq_special_center"><title>Special Centers</title></qandadiv>

<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
      My <link linkend="array_order">array order</link> isn't associated
      with a <link linkend="special_center">special center</link>, but 
      it should be.  Why?  How can I correct it?
    </para>
  </question>
  <answer>
    <para>
      Array orders should be associated with special centers when you
      initially request the order.  If you do not see the option for 
      the special center that you are a part of, you need to contact 
      the <link linkend="special_center_administrator_user">special 
      center administrator</link> or the <link
      linkend="administrator_user">administrator</link> so that you 
      can be designated as a member of the special center in &product;.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the order has already been created and is not associated with
      the special center, you will have to contact the administrator for
      assistance in correcting the problem.
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry>

</qandaset>
</part>
