<part id="user_gui">
<title>Member Home: The User GUI Tool</title>
<article id="array_study_management">

<title>Array Study Management</title>
<sect1 id="create_new_array_study">
<title>Create new array study</title>
<para>
Clicking on the create link, will take you to
the page for editing studies, but the "Array Study Name" will be blank.  
Fill in the name for your study and then proceed with configuration as
described in <link linkend="edit_or_delete_an_existing_array_study">help
for editing an existing array study</link>.
For an overview of the process of creating studies and orders, see <link
linkend="placing_an_order_with_the_array_center">Placing an Order with
the Array Center</link>.  
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="edit_or_delete_an_existing_array_study">
<title>Edit/Delete an existing array study</title>
<para>
Use this link when you wish to edit or delete an <link
linkend="array_study">array study</link>.  See <link
linkend="placing_an_order_with_the_array_center">Placing an Order with
the Array Center</link> for an overview of the process of defining
studies and placing associated <link linkend="array_order">array
orders</link>.
</para>
<para>
To delete an array study, click on the "Delete Array Study" button
associated with the study you wish to delete.  Note that you will not be
able to delete the study if it contains an <link
linkend="experiment_condition">experimental condition</link> that is in
use (has data loaded).  If you are allowed to delete the study, you will
be taken to a confirmation screen where you can verify that you wish to
delete the study.</para>
<para>
To edit the study, choose the "Edit Array Study" button associated with
the study you wish to edit.  From the resulting page, you access two
configuration pages: the "Edit Array Study" page and the "Edit Study
Components" page.  
</para>
<para>
If you do not see the study you wish to edit as an available choice, it
means that you are unable to write changes to the study.  Most likely,
you are not in a group that has write permissions for the study.
</para>
<formalpara>
<title>Edit Array Study</title>
This page is divided into several sections.  The "Edit Study Configuration"
configuration allows configuration of information associated with the study.
The "Edit Defaults for Conditions and Samples Associated with this
Study" section allows users to set values that will be used
repeatedly in editing study components.  In the majority of cases, most
values for experimental conditions and samples within a study are the
same, so setting defaults will save users time in setting individual
values.  &mandatory; Finally, once you have added <link
linkend="experiment_condition">experimental conditions</link>, there
will be a table that shows the details for each experimental condition
associated with the study.  Note that once data is loaded, you will no
longer be able to change fields associated with the loaded data.  
</formalpara>
<para>
The following fields can be configured on the Edit Array Study page:
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
  Study Name</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This name identifies the array study.  Currently, it must be unique across 
the system.  Use the "Names In Use" link allows you to determine what 
study names are in use.  Study names can be up to 128 characters in
length, but longer names do not display well on all pages, so users are
advised to select names around 30 characters in length.  Once data is
loaded for your study, you will no longer be able to change the name.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Study Owner/Group</term>
<listitem>
<para>
The array study owner/group field identifies the 
<link linkend="primary_investigator">PI/</link><link
linkend="group">PI group</link>  who will own the study. Only
<link linkend="users">users</link> who are PIs are able to own studies.
Once this field is set, the PI cannot be modified.  The group can be
modified by the PI if required via the <link
linkend="change_permissions_for_array_studies">Change permissions for
array studies</link> link.  Most users have only one PI, so will have
only one option here (unless their PI has several groups).
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Start Date</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This is the date that study was started.  It will default to the current
date if no date is specified.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Classification</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Studies should be classified if possible--classification is used to
search and sort studies.  You cannot add new classifications, but can
email GEOSS administrators to suggest new classifications.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Comments
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
These comments are sometimes displayed near the study names to help
distiguish studies.  Filling out this field is particularly useful 
to array center staff, as they look at many studies. 
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
 Chip Type
 </term>
<listitem>
<para>
This is the default chip type for the study.  Most studies only use one
chip type, so setting this default saves specifying it repeatedly on the
"Edit Study Components" page.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Species
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This field specifies the default species associated with each
experimental condition.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Number of samples per condition (biological replicates)
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This field specifies the default number of samples per experimental
conditions.  Essentially, it indicates the number of biological
replicates for each condition.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Number of chips per sample (chip replicates)
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This field specifies the default number of chips per sample.  This is
the number of chip replicates, or technical replicates, associated with
the sample.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Lab Notebook ID
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This field specifies the default lab notebook ID associated with
samples.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Lab Notebook Owner
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This field specifies the default lab notebook owner associated with
samples.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Sample type for microarray analysis
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This field specifies the default sample type associated with the
experimental condition.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Sample Origin
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This field specifies the default sample origin associated with samples.
Sample origin is used to make data more meaningful and is used later to
supply MIAME information if you choose to publish your study in GEOSS.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Sample Manipulation
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This field specifies the default sample manipulation associated with samples.
Sample manipulation is used to make data more meaningful and is used later to
supply MIAME information if you choose to publish your study in
&product;.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Experimental Condition Name</term>
<listitem>
<para>
  This is your name for the experimental condition.  
  It used to clarify the design of the study.  Additionally, if you
  choose to <link
  linkend="publishing_your_data">publish your data</link> through
  &product;, your experimental conditions will be identified using the
  name you specify here.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Short name</term>
<listitem>
<para>
  The <link linkend="array_center">array center</link> requires a short
  name for each experimental condition.  This name is used to label
  samples when they are brought to the lab for processing.  It is also
  used in the filename of <link linkend="chip_data_files">data
  files</link> created by the <link
  linkend="array_center_staff_user">array center staff user</link> and
  is included in the &product; hybridization naming convention.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Species</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This is the species associated with the experimental condition.  If the
appropriate species is not listed, please contact <link
linkend="&product;_developers">&product; Developers</link>.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Sample Type for Microarray Analysis
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
  This field describes the sample type associated with the experimental
  condition.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Notes
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
  This is a descriptive field.  It is used only if you choose to publish
  your study results in &product;.  In that case, this information is
  used, along with the experimental condition names to populate the
  <link linkend="miame">MIAME</link> experimental factors field.  You
  will still have an opportunity to modify the description of the
  experimental factors when you publish your data.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>


<varlistentry>
<term>
  Description
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This description can be used to specify additional information about an
experimental condition.  It is used only for display purposes.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Sample Name</term>
<listitem>
<para>
  This is a descriptive field used by the user to uniquely identify
  their sample.  This name can be linked to the hybridization name so
  that result files associated with the biological replicates correspond
  to the sample name. 
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Chip Type
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
  This is the chip type associated with the sample.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  # of Chips (replicates)
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
  This is the number of chips associated with this sample.  It
  determines the number of chip replicates.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Lab Book ID
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
  This field identifies the lab book ID associated with the sample.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Lab Book Owner 
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
  This field identifies the lab book owner associated with the lab book.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Sample Origin
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This field specifies the sample origin associated with samples.
Sample origin is used to make data more meaningful and is used later to
supply MIAME information if you choose to publish your study in GEOSS.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
  Sample Manipulation
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This field specifies the sample manipulation associated with samples.
Sample manipulation is used to make data more meaningful and is used later to
supply MIAME information if you choose to publish your study in GEOSS.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>

<para>
To add experimental conditions, specify the number of conditions to add,
and click "Add Experimental Conditions".  To save changes, click "Save Study".  When configuration of
a study is complete, the status (top line) with change to "COMPLETE".
Once the study status is complete, you can "Order Chips from Array
Center" if the installation supports an array center.
</para>
<para>
Clicking on the order button, takes you to the "Order Chips" page.
This page displays a summary of chips associated with the study and
what their order status is.  If they have not yet been ordered, you
can order chips by specifying associated information (PI/PI group,
Special Center Affiliation, Billing code) and clicking the "Submit
Order" button.  This informs the array center that you would like them
to order chips and ready to bring in samples for processing.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1
id="view_all_array_studies">
<title>View All Array Studies</title>
<para>
This link can be used to view a summary of all <link
linkend="array_study">array studies</link> that you have permission to
view.  The summary displays information on the study name, the organism
being studied, the <link linkend="chip">chip(s)</link> used in the
study, and the disease(s) being studied.  
</para>
<para>
Note that you can sort summary information by any column by clicking on
the button in the column header.  To reverse sort, click on the button a
second time.
</para>
<para>
You may also search through the studies and display a subset based on
the search results.  To search on a particular column, click on the
checkbox associated with that column.  Then specify the criteria you
wish to search for in the input areas in the same cell as the checkbox.
</para>
<para>
You can access additional information by clicking on the "Source" or
"Edit" links if they exist.  Alternatively, if the study name is a link,
you can follow it to view full details on the array study configuration.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1
id="view_array_study">
<title>View Array Study</title>
<para>
This link can be used to view details of an <link
linkend="array_study">array study</link> that you have permission to
view.  The page displays information on the study name, the organism
being studied, the <link
linkend="experiment_condition">conditions</link> of the study, 
the <link linkend="chip">chip(s)</link> used in the
study, and the disease(s) being studied.  Additionally, the page provides
a link to analysis result files, if there is an analysis associated with
the study.  There is also a button that provides a quick link to
creating a custom data set using the study data to facilitate customized
analysis of the data.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1
id="change_permissions_for_array_studies">
<title>Change permissions for array studies</title>
<para>
This link can be used to set permissions for <link
linkend="array_study">array studies</link>.  Note that only <link
linkend="primary_investigator">PIs</link> can change group ownership and
read/write permissions for their studies.  If you are not a PI, then you
will have no studies listed under this link.
</para>
<para>
The following items can be configured:
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Group
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This can be used to change the <link linkend="group">group</link> that
the study is associated with.  The permissions on the <link
linkend="array_study">array study</link> apply to this group only.
Anyone who is not a member of the group will not have permissions to see
the study.  Anyone who is a member will have the permissions set here
applied to them.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Group Read
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This will allow <link linkend="users">users</link> who are part of the
group associated with the array study to read details pertaining to this
study.  This means that they will be able to see the <link
linkend="chip_data_files">chip data files</link> associated with the
study, but they cannot modify the study. 
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Group Write
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This will allow <link linkend="users">users</link> who are part of the
group associated with the array study to write details pertaining to this
study.  This will allow them to modify the array study definition.  They
could, for example, add an <link
linkend="experiment_condition">experimental condition</link>.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para> 
</sect1>

<sect1 id="load_a_study">
<title>Load a study</title>
<para>
This link can be used to load an <link linkend="array_study">
array study</link>.  Note that this link is only available if your
installation allows users to load data.
To load a study, the study data file must first be
uploaded via the <link linkend="upload_a_file">Upload a file</link>
page.  Data file format should be a <link
linkend="single_data_file">single data file</link> containing signal 
values for all hybridizations in the study.  Once a file is uploaded, it
will be available in the list of files to load from.  You must also
select the name of the array study that you are loading.  Only studies
that have a "COMPLETE" status can be loaded.  
</para>
<para>
Once you have selected the study and data file, select "Load Data".  You
will receive an email when the data load is complete.  The loaded data
can then be used for analysis and publishing.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="create_publishing_information">
<title>Create publishing information</title>
<para>
This link can be used to initiation publication of <link
linkend="array_study">array study</link> data. For an overview of the
publication process, see the <link linkend="publishing_your_data">Publishing
your Data</link>  link.
</para>
<para>
On this page, you must specify initial information on the data you wish
to publish.  &mandatory;
</para>
<variablelist>

<varlistentry>
<term>
Miame Name
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This is the name that your publishing information is stored under.  It
should correspond to one experiment.  It is used to identify this set of
publishing information when you return to edit it using <link
linkend="edit_or_delete_or_submit_publishing_information">Edit/Delete/Submit
publishing information</link>.
</para>
<para>
Furthermore, this name will be used, in conjunction with the name of the
owner of the data, as a header for published data.  It also is a
component of the url for the published data.  If you wish to publish a
direct url to your study, you may wish to use underscores instead of
spaces in the name to make the url easier to remember (as spaces are
converted to special characters within the url).</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
Miame Description
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This description should summarize important information (like species
and intent of experiment) about the array study you are publishing.  The
description will appear in a summary table of all published experiments
and provided those who are browsing through the list with a brief
description of your experiment.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
Associated Study
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
If your study is tracked in the local &product; system, select it from the
list.  This allows the system to fill in some of the miame data for you
from your existing study definition and will save you from having to
type duplicate information.  Additionally, it provides &product;
information about the ownership information for the array study so that
you do not need to specify it manually.
If your study is
not tracked by the system, then do not choose an associated study, but
make sure to select a <link
linkend="primary_investigator">PI</link>/<link linkend="group">PI group</link> 
who owns the data.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
PI/PI group
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
You must select the PI/PI group that owns the information you intend to
publish if you have not selected an associated study.
  The published information for the array study will be filed
under the PI's name and the PI will be contacted to verify the desire to
publish the information. 
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
Experiment type
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
<link linkend="miame">MIAME</link> standards require that different
information is stored depending on the type of experiment.  Depending on
the type of experiment specified here, you will be prompted to enter the
appropriate types of MIAME information.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>
Once you have completed the necessary fields, click 'Next'.  This will
take you to the page that allows you to <link
linkend="edit_or_delete_or_submit_publishing_information">edit MIAME
data</link> for the array study.
</para>
<para>
You only need to go through this create process once.  After you have
created the MIAME record you can return to editing it via the <link
linkend="edit_or_delete_or_submit_publishing_information">Edit/Submit/Delete
Publishing Information</link> link.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="edit_or_delete_or_submit_publishing_information">
<title>Edit/Delete/Submit publishing information</title>
<para>
This link allows you to edit, delete, and submit publishing information
for an <link linkend="array_study">array study</link>.
</para>
<formalpara>
<title>Editing and Submitting publishing information
</title>
To edit publishing information, click the "Edit" button for the
appropriate study.  The fields on the resulting page allow you to
specify the appropriate <link linkend="miame">MIAME</link> information
for the the kind of array study data that you are publishing.  It is
important to provide thorough information about your study so that the
data is meaningful.  If you associated the publishing information with
and existing array study, many of the fields will have default values,
taken from your array study configuration.  You may modify these
defaults. Help is available for each of the fields on the page itself,
just click on the help link beside each question to see a description of
what the question means.  To remove the help popup, just click on the
page outside of the popup. 
</formalpara>
<para>
If you are not yet ready to publish your data, but plan to continue
editing at another time, select 'Save form'.  If you have finished
providing the MIAME information and are ready to publish the results,
click 'Submit information'.</para>
<para>
Once you submit the information, the <link
linkend="public_data_administrator">public data administrator</link> is
emailed.  Once they have verified the intent to publish data with the
owner of the data, they will post the appropriate files on the public
data part of the site.  Data is now available for use by all.
</para>
<para>
If you wish to modify some of the descriptive information after the data
has been published, you may do so.  Simply return to the edit page, make
the changes, and re-submit the information.</para>

<formalpara>
<title>Deleting publishing information
</title>
If you have not previous submitted the publishing information, then you
can delete it.  To do this, simply click on the "Delete" button for the
appropriate array study.
</formalpara>
<para>
If you wish to delete a study that has already been published, you will
need to contact the &product; <link
linkend="administrator_user">administrator</link> for assistance.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="view_all_array_orders">
<title>View all array orders</title>
<para>
This page provides a brief view of all <link
linkend="array_order">array orders</link> that you have permission to
see.  Note that you will see information for all orders
associated with <link linkend="group">groups</link> that you are a
member of that have the appropriate read permissions.  Typically, you
will not be able to edit orders.  Occasionally, <link
linkend="array_center_staff_user">array center staff</link> may unlock an
order so that you can edit components of the order via the <link
linkend="edit_or_delete_an_existing_array_study">Edit/Delete an Existing
Array Study</link> interface.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="change_permissions_for_array_orders">
<title>Change permissions for array orders</title>
<para>
This link can be used to set permissions for <link
linkend="array_order">array orders</link>.  Note that only <link
linkend="primary_investigator">PIs</link> can change group ownership and
read/write permissions for their orders.  If you are not a PI, then you
will have no orders listed under this link.
</para>
<para>
The following items can be configured:
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Group
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This can be used to change the <link linkend="group">group</link> that
the order is associated with.  The permissions on the <link
linkend="array_order">array order</link> apply to this group only.
Anyone who is not a member of the group will not have permissions to see
the order.  Anyone who is a member will have the permissions set here
applied to them.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Group Read
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This will allow <link linkend="users">users</link> who are part of the
group associated with the array order to read details pertaining to this
order.  This means that they will be able to see the <link
linkend="chip_data_files">chip data files</link> associated with the
order, but they cannot modify the order. 
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Group Write
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This will allow <link linkend="users">users</link> who are part of the
group associated with the array order to write details pertaining to this
order. Typically array orders are locked, so users will be unable to
write changes to orders even if they have write permission.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>
</sect1>
</article>


<article id="file_management">
<title>File Management</title>
<sect1 id="view_my_files">
<title>View my files</title>
<para>
This link provides <link linkend="users">users</link> with the ability
to view their <link linkend="user_file">files</link>.  Users can have several types of files including
<link linkend="chip_data_files">chip data files</link>, <link
linkend="analysis_files">analysis files</link>, and <link
linkend="uploaded_files">uploaded files</link>.  
All files can be viewed and downloaded from
this location.
</para>
<para>
Files can be viewed in one of two modes: directory tree mode or current
directory only mode.  Both views allow users to see all files and
which mode to use is entirely a matter of personal preference.  The
directory tree mode shows the entire tree structure, which is more
intuitive to many users.  The current directory mode is slightly faster,
however, which may be useful to users who must navigate a large number
of files (<link linkend="array_center_staff_user">array center
staff</link>). To switch between the two modes, click on
the "View Current Directory Only" button or the "View Entire Directory
Tree" button as appropriate.
</para>
<para>
The "View my files" page is divided into three distinct parts:
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Directory Navigation
    </term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      Regardless of the mode you use, you can navigate through the directory
      structure by clicking on the names of directories.  Note that in the
      "Current Directory Only" view, ".." will
      take you up a directory and the "top" will take
      you to the top level directory for the current user.  In "Directory
      Tree" view, the current directory is highlighted in yellow.
      Only the files in
      your current directory are displayed in the file viewer.
    </para>
    <para>
      The directory structure format is fixed.  The top level contains <link
      linkend="&product;_login_id">&product; login ids</link> for every user
      who has files that you can see (i.e. you are in one of their groups).
      Under each user directory, you may see the following directories:

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            Data_Files
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
  This directory contains subdirectories for each finished <link
  linkend="array_order">array order</link> owned by the user.  The
  subdirectories are named after the <link
  linkend="order_number">order number</link> and contain the <link
  linkend="chip_data_files">chip data files</link> associated with that
  order.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            Analysis_Files
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
  This directory contains subdirectories for each <link
  linkend="analysis_tree">analysis tree</link> owned by the user.  The
  subdirectories are named after the tree and contain the <link
  linkend="analysis_files">analysis files</link> associated with that
  tree.
            </para>
          </listitem>
         </varlistentry>

         <varlistentry>
           <term>
             Upload
           </term>
             <listitem>
               <para>
  This directory contains <link linkend="uploaded_files">uploaded 
  files</link>.  Depending on what files the
  user has uploaded, there can be several subdirectories including:
  criteria, data, mas5, other, logo, and icon.  Uploaded files are found in the
  appropriate subdirectory based on the type specified during the upload. 
               </para>
              </listitem>
             </varlistentry>

           </variablelist>
         </para>

       </listitem>
     </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
     <term>
       File Viewer
     </term>
     <listitem>
       <para>
  The file viewing component of the page displays all files in the current
  directory.  You can view the file by clicking on the filename.  If your
  browser understands how to display that file type, it will show it to
  you.  Otherwise it will download it to your computer.  Note that some
  downloads may be time consuming as some of chip data files are very
  large.
       </para>

       <para>
  Some files may be deleted.  Raw data files may not be deleted, but analysis
  files and uploaded files can be.  To delete a file, click on the trash
  can icon on the far right that is associated with the file.  Note that
  the quickest way to delete analysis files is to delete the entire
  analysis using <link
  linkend="edit_or_delete_or_run_an_existing_analysis_tree">Edit/Delete/Run
  an existing analysis tree</link>.
       </para>
       <para>
  The list of files displayed can be filtered using the "Filename Pattern"
  field.  To use this field type in the pattern that the filename must
  contain and click "Select".  This pattern will apply until you clear the
  "Filename Pattern" field and click "Select" again.  For instance, if you
  only wish to see files of type "txt" in the "Filename Pattern" and click
  "Select".  The view will be filtered accordingly.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry>
       <term>
         Navigation Short Cuts
       </term>
       <listitem>
         <para>
  The short cuts are an alternative technique for navigating through
  directories and a provide quick ways to navigate to commonly viewed i
  areas.  There are four short cuts:
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
             <term>
               View Files Owned By
             </term>
             <listitem>
             <para>
  If you are in several <link linkend="group">groups</link>, it is often
  useful to look only at files owned by a specific user.  This short cut
  is particularly useful to <link
  linkend="administrator_user">administrators</link> and <link
  linkend="array_center_staff_user">array center staff</link>.
             </para>
             </listitem>
           </varlistentry>

           <varlistentry>
           <term>
             View Files Associated with Loaded Orders
           </term>
           <listitem>
             <para>
  This short cut allows users to go directly to the directory containing
  chip data files for a specific <link linkend="array_order">array order
  </link>.
             </para>
           </listitem>
           </varlistentry>

           <varlistentry>
             <term>
                View Files Associated with Sample
             </term>
             <listitem>
             <para>
  This short cut allows users to look at all files associated with a
  specific <link linkend="sample">sample</link>.  It allows users to 
  select the sample based on the
  researcher's name for the sample.  The short cut then navigates to the
  appropriate array order directory and uses the array center staff name
  for the sample in the "Filename Pattern" field.  The result is a listing
  of all files associated with that sample.  Note that you will need to
  manually clear the "Filename Pattern" field after using this short cut
  if you wish to view files not associated with the sample.
             </para>
             </listitem>
           </varlistentry>

           <varlistentry>
           <term>
  View Analysis Tree File Results
           </term>
           <listitem>
           <para>
  This short cut allows users to look at all files associated with a
  specific <link linkend="analysis_tree">analysis tree</link>.  
           </para>
           </listitem>
         </varlistentry>

       </variablelist>
  To use a short cut, simple select the desired target and hit the
  associated "Go" button.
     </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1
id="change_permissions_for_files">
<title>Change group ownership and read/write permissions for existing files</title>
<para>
This link can be used to set permissions for <link
linkend="user_file">user files</link>.  
Note that for most data files, permissions will be set correctly given
the permissions for the associated <link linkend="array_order">array 
order</link> or <link linkend="array_study">array study</link>.  
However, you may occasionally wish to change permissions
on certain files so that other users in your <link
linkend="group">groups</link> can see them.  Note that this page can get
lengthy.  Files are arranged alphabetically.
</para>
<para>
The following items can be configured:
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Group
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This can be used to change the <link linkend="group">group</link> that
the file is associated with.  The permissions on the <link
linkend="user_file">user file</link> apply to this group only.
Anyone who is not a member of the group will not have permissions to see
the file.  Anyone who is a member will have the permissions set here
applied to them.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Group Read
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This will allow <link linkend="users">users</link> who are part of the
group associated with the file to see and download the file.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Group Write
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This allows <link linkend="users">users</link> 
who are part of the
group associated with the file to 
write to the file.
In actuality, this provides very limited permissions.  No users are
allowed to overwrite or delete <link linkend="chip_data_files">chip data
files</link>, so no permissions are granted for this type of file.
Users can't overwrite other users' <link
linkend="analysis_files">analysis files</link> or <link
linkend="uploaded_files">uploaded files</link>.  This permission would
allow users in your group to delete your analysis files and uploaded
files though.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="upload_a_file">
<title>Upload a File</title>
<para>
This link allows <link linkend="users">users</link> to upload <link
linkend="uploaded_files">files</link>.  Typically uploaded files are
used to in association with data analysis.  For an overview of this 
process, see <link linkend="determining_tree_input">Determining Tree 
Input</link>.  To upload a file, you must first specify the type of 
file you wish to upload.  Several types have very specific formats 
that must be adhered to.  Possible upload types include:
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
    data
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
      This filetype allows users to upload a file that contains
      all data for an <link linkend="array_study">array_study</link>.
      Data should be in the <link linkend="single_data_file">single data
      file</link> format.  Uploading a file of this type makes it
      available for users to <link linkend="load_a_study">load a
      study</link>.  Note that users may not be able to load studies on
      all installations.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>
    mas5
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
      Users may upload <link linkend="microarray_suite">mas5</link>
      data for individuals chips. This will result in the creation of a
      hybridization and the chip data will be loaded into the database.
      The data will then be available for use in <link 
      linkend="analysis_condition">analysis conditions</link>.   File
      format for this kind of upload is a <link
      linkend="affymetrix_txt_file">Affymetrix mas5 txt
      file</link>Affymetrix mas5 txt file.  The
      following fields must be specified when uploading mas5 data:
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            Hybridization Name
         </term>
         <listitem>
           <para>
        This field needs to be filled out if a mas5 file is being
        uploaded.  The <link linkend="hybridization">hybridization</link> 
        name, combined with the upload
        timestamp provides a unique identifier for the uploaded data.
        The name will be used when including uploaded hybridizations in
        analysis conditions.
           </para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>
           Affymetrix Chip
         </term>
         <listitem>
           <para>
        This field needs to be filled out if a mas5 file is being
        uploaded.  As a hybridization is being created, it is necessary
        to know the <link linkend="layout">layout</link> (chip type).  If the 
        correct chip type is not in the drop down box, contact the
        <link linkend="administrator_user">administrator</link> for
        assistance.
           </para>
          </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
       </variablelist>
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
    analysis input
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
      This filetype allows users to upload a file that is already 
      appropriately formatted for use by analysis trees.  This is 
      useful if you wish to analyze results for currently unsupported
      data types, such as <link linkend="cdna">cDNA</link> data.
      See <link linkend="uploading_external_experiment_data">Uploading
      external experiment data</link> for a description of this format.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>
    criteria
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
      <link linkend="criteria_file">Criteria files</link> can be used
      to facilitate creation of analysis conditions and <link
      linkend="analysis_set">analysis sets</link>. 
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
    other
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
      This file type can be used up upload any other type of file.
      Uploading files of this type will have no effect on GEOSS, except
      to store the file and make it available via the <link
      linkend="view_my_files">View My Files</link>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
Regardless of which file type you choose, you will be asked to specify 
the following:
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Filename
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
      This field is optional.  If you wish to give the file a different
      name than the name it has on the source system, you may specify
      that name in the filename field.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      File to Upload
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Specify the appropriate file to upload from your local machine.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>

Once all fields have been configured, click "Upload".  Please note that
loading a very large data file may take several minutes.  If the file is
too large, your browser may time out and return an error.  This error
reflects a timeout on the part of the browser, but does not necessarily
mean that the file failed to load.  Wait for a bit and then check
whether the file has been loaded via the <link
linkend="view_my_files">View My Files</link> link.  All uploaded files
should be accessible from that interface.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="view_quality_control_records">
<title>View Quality Control records</title>
<para>
To view the quality control information for a specific <link
linkend="hybridization">hybridization</link>, select the hybridization
from the drop down list and click "View QC".  The quality control data
is taken from the <link linkend="chip_data_files">chip data files</link>
generated while running the array experiment.  Note that not all
hybridizations will have quality control data as the appropriate files
may not have been present when the data was loaded.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="create_a_data_file_containing_all_data_for_one_study">
<title>Create a data file containing all data for one study</title>
<para>
This link will create a data file that contains the signal values for
all hybridizations is a specific study.  This file is very similar in
format to the files used as input to analysis trees.  
</para>
<para>Provide a filename and comments.  Choose the <link
linkend="array_study">array study</link> you wish to obtain data from
from the drop down box.  Note that only studies that have all their
associated data loaded are listed in the box as you clearly cannot get
data for a study that has none loaded.  Choose "Create Data File".  The
resulting data file will be loaded under your <link
linkend="&product;_login_id">login id</link> in the <link
linkend="view_my_files">file viewer</link>.</para>

</sect1>
</article>

<article id="analysis_management">
<title>Analysis Management</title>
<sect1 id="create_or_run_a_new_analysis_tree">
<title>Create/Run a new Analysis Tree</title>
<para>
This link allows <link linkend="users">users</link> to create new
<link linkend="analysis_tree">analysis trees</link>.  For an overview of
analysis trees, see <link
linkend="analyzing_data_using_analysis_trees">Analyzing your data
using analysis trees</link>.
</para>
<para>
When you create a new tree, you must specify the name, the desired
initial structure, and the source of input.
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Analysis Tree Name
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This name must be unique.  Use the "Show list of used tree names" link
to determine uniqueness.  A combination of the analysis creation date
and the input data name tends to be a useful naming convention.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
Tree Structure
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
The "Initial node only" setting will result in your tree having only one
node, "Quality Control", when it is created.  For there you can go on to
add additional nodes as necessary.  The "Entire default tree" setting
results in the tree's initial structure consisting of several nodes in
an arrangement that is typically used by &product; analysis staff. 
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
Analysis Input Data Source
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
To select a source, click on the radio button to the left of the desired
source type, then click "Choose Source".  All sources of the applicable
type will be displayed in a table below the source radio buttons.
Select the desired source for the tree.  For an overview of the
different source types (array study, analysis set, and public data), see
<link linkend="determining_tree_input">Determining Tree Input</link>.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>
Once you have set the appropriate values, click "Next" to create the
tree and proceed to the
<link
linkend="edit_or_delete_or_run_an_existing_analysis_tree">Edit/Delete/Run
an existing analysis tree</link> page where you can refine the
configuration of the new tree.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="edit_or_delete_or_run_an_existing_analysis_tree">
<title>Edit/Delete/Run an existing Analysis Tree</title>
<para>
This link allows <link linkend="users">users</link> to edit, delete or
run existing 
<link linkend="analysis_tree">analysis trees</link>.  For an overview of
analysis trees, see <link
linkend="analyzing_data_using_analysis_trees">Analyzing your data
using analysis trees</link>.
</para>
<formalpara>
<title>
Editing an existing analysis tree
</title>
The current node is the node that is highlighted in yellow.  All
configuration activities are performed on the current node.  To change
the current node, click on the pencil icon for node that you wish to
make current.  Configuring a tree involves several steps:
<variablelist>

<varlistentry>
<term>
Adding Nodes
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
To add a new node to the tree, select the type of analysis from the
"Choose" drop down list and click "Add Node".  The new analysis node
will use the output of the current node as input.  Note that the list
of possible analyses to add is restricted by the current node selection.
The list only contains analyses that can use the output of the current
node as input.
</para>
<para>
Only current versions of <link linkend="analysis">analyses</link> 
are available in the "Choose" box (the version number is indicated by
the number behind the analysis name).  
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
Deleting Nodes
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Nodes can be deleted by clicking on the trash can icon on the node.
This will delete the node and all nodes below it in the tree structure.
There is currently no confirmation, the nodes are just deleted.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
Configuring Nodes
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
The configuration parameters for the current node are located on the
right hand portion of the page.  The parameters vary, based on the type
of analysis.  To obtain help on the parameters of each analysis, look at
the help page for that analysis.  It can be accessed by clicking on the
name of the analysis inside the node.
</para>
<para>
The default tree should run successfully using the default values for
each parameter.  
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</formalpara>
<formalpara>
<title>
Deleting an existing analysis tree
</title>
To delete an analysis tree, click on the "delete" button for the
appropriate tree.  Note that if the tree has been run, this will delete
all associated input and output files (but not the actual <link
linkend="chip_data_files">chip data files</link> used to generate the
input file).
</formalpara>
<formalpara>
<title>
Running an existing analysis tree
</title>
Once the analysis tree has been configured, it can be run by clicking
the "Run Analysis" button.  This runs the tree, which typically takes a
non-trivial amount of time.  The actual amount of time depends largely
on which nodes are included in the tree, the size of the input data
set and the other load on the system while the analysis tree is being
run. To provide a very general guideline, it takes about fifteen minutes
to run the default tree on a data set that includes nine MG_U74Av2
chips.  Large analyses can often take over a day to run.
</formalpara>
<para>
Note that is some cases, after a new &product; release, the nodes in
your tree may become obsolete.  This relates to upgrading the node, the
R version, or R libraries.  If your tree contains obsolete nodes, the
"Run Analysis" button will not be present, as you cannot run obsolete
trees.  However, the "Upgrade Tree" and "Copy Tree" buttons should
appear.  These buttons can be used to upgrade the tree, if possible.
The "Upgrade Tree" button upgrades all obsolete nodes in the tree.  If
this action is successful, the "Run Analysis" button will reappear and
you can run your tree again.  Note that your result files from the older
version of the tree will be overwritten.  If you wish to preserve the
results files from the older version, you can copy the tree instead of
upgrading.  This creates a copy of the old tree, then upgrades the
versions on the copy.  You then have two versions of the tree: an older
one containing obsolete nodes and a new, upgraded one.  When you run the
new one, the old tree is unaffected, so you can still access the result
files.  All trees have an associated "versions.txt" file that shows the
versions of softward that the tree results were generated with.
</para>
<para>
Due to the large amount of time involved in running trees,
 &product; will send you an
email to notify you when the analysis is complete and the completion
status.  <link linkend="analysis_files">Analysis result files</link> can
be viewed via the <link linkend="view_my_files">View My Files</link>.
Note the navigational short cut at  the bottom of the "View My Files"
page that will take you directly to the results for a specific tree.  If
the tree did not complete successfully, see the <link
linkend="troubleshooting_tree_failures">Troubleshooting tree 
failures</link> link for guidance.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="create_new_analysis_condition">
<title>Create new analysis condition</title>
<para>
This link allows <link linkend="users">users</link> to create new
<link linkend="analysis_condition">analysis conditions</link>. 
For an overview of this process, see <link
linkend="determining_tree_input">Determining tree input</link>.
</para>
<para>
To create a new analysis condition, specify the condition name and
description.  As many analysis conditions can represent the same data
(if many analyses are performed), it is helpful to provide a description
even though it is not mandatory.  Also choose the <link
linkend="primary_investigator">PI</link>/<link linkend="group">PI
group</link> that will own the condition.  This will allow others in the
group to use the analysis condition.  Click 'Next' to create the
analysis condition.  Then you will be ready to specify which
hybridizations to include in the analysis condition.
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="edit_existing_analysis_conditions">
<title>Edit existing analysis conditions</title>
<para>
This link allows <link linkend="users">users</link> to edit existing
<link linkend="analysis_condition">analysis conditions</link>.  
For an overview of this process, see <link
linkend="determining_tree_input">Determining tree input</link>.
</para>
<para>
This page allows <link linkend="users">users</link> to modify
<link linkend="hybridization">hybridizations</link> included 
in the analysis condition.  To add hybridizations, choose the desired
analysis condition and click "Add Hybridization". Click on the desired
source, then click "Choose hybridization" source.  The use of each
source is as follows:
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
    Analysis Conditions
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
      An existing analysis condition can be used as the source for
      hybridizations.  If this source is used, a list of analysis
      conditions you have permissions to read is displayed.  You may
      select one or more analysis conditions by checking the checkbox
      beside the condition name.  All hybridizations in all selected
      analysis conditions will be included in the current analysis
      condition once you click "Add hybrids to Condition".
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
    Studies
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
      An existing <link linkend="array_study">array study</link> may be 
      used as the source for hybridizations.  If this source is used, a 
      list of array studies you have permission to use is displayed.
      You may select one or more studies.  All hybridizations in all
      selected studies will be included in the current analysis
      condition once you click "Add hybrids to Condition".
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Experimental Conditions
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
      An existing <link linkend="experiment_condition">experimental
      condition</link> may be used as the source for hybridizations.  If
      this source is used, a list of experimental conditions that you
      have permission to use is displayed.  You may select one or more
      experimental conditions.  All hybridizations in all selected
      experimental conditions will be included in the current analysis
      condition once you click "Add hybrids to Condition".
      </para>
      <note>
      Experimental conditions are easily confused with analysis
      conditions as analysis conditions are derived from experimental
      conditions.  Remember that experimental conditions are defined as
      part of an array study and are used by array orders.  They relate
      to a specific experimental intent and are unchanging.  Analysis
      conditions often mimic experimental conditions (as we wish to
      analyze data based on the intent of the experiment).  However
      analysis condition is entirely theoretical and is subject to
      change.  Users can change the grouping of hybridizations in
      analysis conditions at any time.</note>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Hybridizations
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
      Existing hybridizations may also be
      used as the source for hybridizations.  If this source is used, a 
      list of hybridizations you can read is displayed.
      You may select one or more hybridizations.  All hybridizations 
      selected will be included in the current analysis
      condition once you click "Add hybrids to Condition". 
      </para>
      <note>This option provides direct access to hybridizations that
      have been created by uploading a mas5 data file.</note>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      From Criteria File
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
      This is an advanced option for selecting hybridizations.  See
      <link linkend="using_criteria_files">Using criteria files</link>
      for a conceptual background of this process.  To use this source,
      you will first need to upload an appropriate criteria file using the
      <link linkend="upload_a_file">Upload a file </link> link
      available from <link linkend="user_gui">&mem_home;</link>.  If
      this has been done, the criteria filename should appear in the
      drop down box.  Select the appropriate file, then click "Get
      Criteria File".
      </para>
      <para>
      If the criteria file is well formed, a selection of <link
      linkend="continuous_parameter">Continuous Parameters</link> and/or
      <link linkend="categorical_parameter">Categorical
      Parameters</link> will be displayed.  Use this selection interface
      to specify which hybridizations you want included.  Hybridizations
      will be added to the analysis condition when you click "Add
      Hybrids to Condition".
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

</variablelist>
Once you have added the hybridizations to the analysis condition, you
are returned to the the Edit Analysis Condition page and can view the
hybridizations that are currently part of the analysis condition.
Hybridizations can be removed from the analysis condition by checking
the "Delete" checkbox and hitting "Update".
</para>
<para>
When the configuration of the analysis condition is satisfactory, you
can return to <link linkend="user_gui">&mem_home;</link> via the header
links at the top of the page.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="create_new_set_of_conditions">
<title>Create new set of conditions</title>
<para>
This link allows <link linkend="users">users</link> to create new
<link linkend="analysis_set">analysis set</link>.  
For an overview of this process, see <link
linkend="determining_tree_input">Determining tree input</link>.
</para>
<para>
To create a new analysis set, specify the condition name and
description.  As many analysis sets can represent the same data
(if many analyses are performed), it is helpful to provide a description
even though it is not mandatory.  Also choose the <link
linkend="primary_investigator">PI</link>/<link linkend="group">PI
group</link> that will own the analysis set.  This will allow others in the
group to use the analysis set.  Click 'Next' to create the
analysis set.  Then you will be ready to specify which
conditions to include in the analysis set.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="edit_existing_set_of_conditions">
<title>Edit existing set of conditions</title>
<para>
This page allows <link linkend="users">users</link> to modify
<link linkend="analysis_condition">analysis conditions</link> included 
in the set of analysis conditions.  To add conditions, choose the desired
analysis set.   From the "Edit Set of Conditions" page, click "Add
Conditions". Click on the desired
source, then click "Choose Condition Source" button.  The use of each
source is as follows:
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
    Analysis Conditions
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
      An existing analysis condition can be used as the source for
      analysis conditions.  If this source is used, a list of analysis
      conditions you can read is displayed.  You may
      select one or more analysis conditions by checking the checkbox
      beside the condition name.  All selected
      analysis conditions will be included in the current analysis
      set once you click "Add Conditions".
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
    Studies
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
      An existing <link linkend="array_study">array study</link> may be 
      used as the source for analysis conditions.  If this source is used, a 
      list of array studies you can read is displayed.
      You may select one or more studies.  Analysis conditions are
      automatically created that correspond to all <link
      linkend="experiment_condition">experimental conditions</link> that
      are part of the study. The new analysis conditions are included in
      the current analysis set once you click "Add Conditions".
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Experimental Conditions
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
      Existing <link linkend="experiment_condition">experimental
      conditions</link> may be used as the source for analysis sets.  If
      this source is used, a list of experimental conditions that you
      have can read is displayed.  You may select one or more
      experimental conditions.  Analysis conditions are automatically
      created that correspond to all checked experimental conditions.
      The new analysis conditions are included in the current analysis
      set once you click "Add Conditions".
      </para>
      <note>
      Experimental conditions are easily confused with analysis
      conditions as analysis conditions are derived from experimental
      conditions.  Remember that experimental conditions are defined as
      part of an array study and are used by array orders.  They relate
      to a specific experimental intent and are unchanging.  Analysis
      conditions often mimic experimental conditions (as we wish to
      analyze data based on the intent of the experiment).  However
      analysis condition is entirely theoretical and is subject to
      change.  Users can change the grouping of hybridizations in
      analysis conditions at any time.</note>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      From Criteria File
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
      This is an advanced option for selecting hybridizations.  See
      <link linkend="using_criteria_files">Using criteria files</link>
      for a conceptual background of this process.  To use this source,
      you will first need to upload an appropriate criteria file using the
      <link
      linkend="upload_a_file">Upload a file</link> link
      available from <link linkend="user_gui">&mem_home;</link>.  If
      this has been done, the criteria filename should appear in the
      drop down box.  Select the appropriate file, then click "Get
      Criteria File".
      </para>
      <para>
      If the criteria file is well formed, it will specify a grouping of
      hybridizations into analysis conditions.  Those conditions will be
      automatically inserted into the set.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

</variablelist>
Once you have added the analysis condition to the analysis set, you
are returned to the the Edit Analysis Set page and can view the
analysis conditions that are currently part of the analysis set.
Analysis conditions can be removed from the analysis set by checking
the "Delete" checkbox and hitting "Update".
</para>
<para>
When the configuration of the analysis set is satisfactory, you
can return to <link linkend="user_gui">&mem_home;</link> via the header
links at the top of the page.</para>
</sect1>
</article>

<article id="account_management">
<title>Account Management</title>
<sect1 id="update_my_personal_info">
<title>Update my personal info</title>
<para>
Initial account information is set when the account is initially
created.  To update information change the appropriate values in the
appropriate fields, and click "submit".  Note that you can't change your
<link linkend="users">user type</link>.  This information is provided
for informational purposes only.
</para>
<para>
It is particularly important to keep your name, phone number, and email
address up-to-date as this information is used by &product; and <link
linkend="array_center_staff_user">array center staff</link> to
communicate with you.  
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="change_my_password">
<title>Change my password</title>
<para>
To change your password, simply enter your old and new <link
linkend="password">password</link> in the appropriate fields.
&password_rule;
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="create_a_new_group">
<title>Create a new group</title>
<para>
This link allows <link linkend="users">users</link> to create new <link
linkend="group">groups</link> to provide control over who can see and
work with their data.  To add a new group, simply click on this link and
specify the name for the new group.  This name should be meaningful to
members of the group.  Then click "Submit".  After creating the group
you can set the members using the <link
linkend="manage_membership_of_my_groups">Manage membership of my
groups</link> link.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="manage_membership_of_my_groups">
<title>Manage membership of my groups</title>
<para>
This link allows users to control which <link
linkend="users">users</link> are part of their <link
linkend="group">groups</link>.  Initially, each user owns one group
(named after their <link linkend="&product;_login_id">login id</link>).  If
necessary, users can create additional groups.  To modify membership in
a group, click this link and the click on the "Manage" button for the
group you wish to edit.  To add users to your group, check the checkboxes
under "Is a member?" that correspond to the appropriate names and login
ids.  To remove users, simply uncheck the appropriate boxes.  When the
configuration is correct, save the changes by clicking "Finish".
</para>
</sect1>
</article>

</part>
